Hello and welcome back to another
exciting tutorial of great stack. In
today's video, we are going to build and
deploy a full stack project management
application using perstack. In this full
stack project, user can sign up and
create their organization or workspace.
In this workspace, you can invite
members, create task, add task, and
assign task to any member. So let's take
a look at the project demo. So once you
will open this application, it will ask
you to sign in or sign up. After sign
up, you need to create an organization.
So once you will sign up, you will see
this popup to create an organization.
And after that, you will see this
dashboard. In this dashboard, you will
find the project details. So this is the
project overview. So here you will find
the list of projects. And in this card
you will find the total number of
projects, completed projects, my task
and overdue projects or task. Now in the
right side we have the task summary. We
have my task then overdue in progress.
Here you will find the recent activities
and after that come to this left
sidebar. Here you will find this
drop-down from where you can change the
organization. You can switch between
different organization or workspace. if
you have multiple workspace right and
you can click on this button to create a
new workspace or organization
and after that let me just click on this
projects so here you will find all the
projects in this organization so if you
open any project
so here you will find the list of task
correct and you can create a new task
using this button create task Right, you
need to enter the details and create a
new task. Let me switch the theme. I'll
open this web page in dark mode. So you
can see it looks beautiful in this dark
mode also.
And this is the light mode. Right? So in
this one we have multiple options like
you can see the list of task, you can
see the calendar. So in this calendar
you will see the due date for the task.
Here you will find the analytics where
you can see the task by status, task by
type and task by priority. In this
settings you can update the project
details. And here you can click here to
invite a new member in this project.
Right? If I come back here in the left
sidebar we have the team. So in this
team we have the invite button. If I
click here, you can invite a new member
in this organization or workspace. You
need to enter the email ID and click
send invitation. Right? Then we have the
settings that will open the profile
settings. Let me switch to light mode.
After that, here in the left side, you
will find the list of task. We can
expand it like this. And here you will
find the list of task. And after that,
here you will find the list of projects
also. Right? If I expand it here, you
have the task, analytics, calendar and
settings for this particular project.
Now let me create a new organization
here. So I'll click on this drop-down
and click on create workspace.
And here we will choose the logo. Then
we'll add the organization name here. So
let me write any organization name. I'll
write the dummy name here or Spotify
inc. and create organization.
So here we have created a new workspace
and you can invite the members in this
workspace. You can enter the email id
and click on send invitation or you can
simply click escape. We can invite the
members later. So after that
you can find the drop-down here and here
you have another organization. Let me
just click here and you can switch the
organization. So now you can see we are
in the new organization and here we
don't have any data right we don't have
any project or task. If I go to project
we don't have any project. If I go to
team we have only one team member right
that is the admin. Let me just click
here invite member and here you can
enter the email ID.
Here you can choose the role. I'll
choose member and click on send
invitation.
Now let me open my email id. So here I
have received this invitation to join
this a Spotify inc workspace and click
on this invitation. So it will ask you
to sign up on this application
and if you already have an account with
this email id you will simply log in and
you will find this organization in your
profile. So you can see in this profile
also I am the member of this Spotify
inc. Right now let me just come back to
the previous account and here it will
create a new project. So I'll just click
on this button new project and here
we'll add the details. So let's add the
project name. So I'll write music a
streaming app and here we will add the
project description and after that you
need to choose the status. So let's add
active. We will choose the priority and
a start date and end date.
And here we'll choose the team lead and
you can also choose the other members
right and click on create project. So we
have created a project here.
And after that you will find the
projects here in this dashboard also and
in this left sidebar also. Let's click
here and you will go to task. So here
you can click on this new task and
create a new task here. So I'll write
the task name like UIUX design.
Then you need to add the task
description and you can choose the type
it is task and priority and you can
assign this to any member. Right? But
you can add the team member also. If I
go to settings and here you can see we
have only one member. Right? So in this
project let me add a new member. So if I
click on this drop-down you can see we
have another member also. Right? Let me
choose this one and click on add member.
So we have added another member in this
project.
Right? You can see now we have two
members in this project. Now let me
create the task. And here we'll add the
task name. And then we will add the task
description here. And let's choose the
type task and priority and assign this
to this user. And then we will add the
uh status to-do or you can choose the in
progress done anything. And here you
need to add the due date and create
task.
So you can see the task list here. One
task has been created. Let me add
another task also. I'll click on this
new task. And here we will add the
description.
Then let me choose the type improvement
or you can choose feature. We can set
the priority assigned to any user and
here we'll add the in progress or to-do.
Then we will choose the due date and
create task. So we have created two
task. Whenever a new task is assigned to
any user then they will receive an email
like this. You can see a new task has
been assigned to this user. And here we
have this email right and the user will
receive another email also that is the
reminder email on the due date if the
task is not completed on the due date.
We can also update the status from this
drop-down. We can click here and choose
done. So we can update the status and we
can also delete the task by using this
checkbox and click on delete. So this
task will be deleted.
Now let me open any task and in this one
we can add the comment also. So let's
add the comment in this discussion. So
I'll write it's completed and click on
post.
So you can see the comment has been
added in this discussion. So this was
the overview of the project management
application. Let me switch the
organization from this drop-down and let
me change the theme also. In this
project, we have created user
authentication and organization
management using color. Color makes it
easy to handle user signin, signup and
account management. With color's
organization feature, we can create an
organization, invite and manage the team
members. We have added inest in this
project to manage the background jobs
and scheduling. Using ingest functions,
we will send the new task assignment and
reminder emails. It will also help us to
handle the color behooks more
efficiently. To store user, organization
and project data, we are going to use
neon. Neon is a serverless Postgress SQL
database that helps developers build
reliable and scalable application
quickly. After building this fullstack
project management application, we will
deploy it online using versel. So if you
are also excited to build your own
project management app, just write down
I'm going to build this project
management app in the comment box. I
will recommend you to build this project
and add the project live link in your
réumé or you can also use it as your
college project. Now let's get started
to build our project management
application. We will use an open-source
template created by great stack. Simply
visit greatstack GitHub profile at
github.com/grastackdev.
On this page you will find a project
called project management. And I will
also provide this repo link in the video
description. So let's open this
repository.
It is a free open-source project
management website template built using
ReactJS and Telvin CSS.
Don't forget to click the star button on
GitHub to support this project. If you
show more love on this project, we will
bring more open-source project for you.
We also have other open-source project
on our GitHub page. You can check out
other projects and hit the start button.
So again come back to this project
management repository
to get started. You can fork the
repository and clone it on your local
machine or simply click the code button
and then choose download zip and
download the zip file.
It has been downloaded. Now let me place
this downloaded zip file on the desktop
screen.
So here we have the downloaded zip file.
Let me extract it. I'll right click and
select
extract here.
So here we have this folder project
management main. Correct. And if I open
this folder here we have the
code file and folder. Correct. Now let
me just come back and I'll place it in a
project folder. So here I'll create the
project folder and write the project
name that is project management.
So we have added the folder called
project management and in this one let's
add this downloaded folder just add it
here
like this. So now let me rename the
folder. So here the folder name is
project management main. So I'll write
client
because this is the front end template
only. So I have added the name client.
Now let's open this project management
folder with VS code.
So now this project management is open
in VS code and here we have the client
folder.
Right after that just right click on
this client
and select open in integrated terminal.
So in this terminal you can see we are
in this client directory. Right. So now
we can start our client project. If I
expand this folder here we have the
public folder then src and other files.
Here we have the index.html file. Then
we have the package.json JSON and then
we config. So let's open this
package.json file.
In this one you can see we have the list
of dependencies like Redux JS Telvin CSS
date function Lucid React. We have added
Lucid React to use the icons and we have
used ReduxJS toolkit to manage the
state. Then we have the React React DOM
and React hot toast. Using this React
hot toast, we can display the toast
notification. Then we have the React
Redux for managing the state and then we
have the React router DOM. So using this
we can navigate the pages and after that
we have the recharts and Telvin CSS.
Now let's open this index.html file. In
this one, you can update the
project title. You can add the favicon
icon here.
Now, let's come here in this public
folder. So, here we have favicon.ico.
That's it. And in this src, we have all
the pages, right? And we have the pages
and components. We have the assets also.
If I expand this assets here, we have
all images and icons that will be used
in this project. And then we have the
assets.js
file. If I open assets.js.
In this one, we have imported all the
images and exported it using this assets
object so that we can easily access it
in our project. Then we have added some
dummy data. As you can see dummy users
then we have dummy workspaces and in
this workspaces you will find the ID
then organization
ID. Then we have the organization name
slug. This is the corp workspace.
After that we have the image URL. So in
this dummy workspaces we have added the
data for different organization
and uh in this organization we have
members
and uh you can see the member ID, user
ID, workspace ID, role, user
and after that in this
organization
we have this projects right and in this
project we can add multiple task. So we
have added the dummy projects members
task.
Here also we have the members. So we can
add multiple members in a project.
Then we have the project owner and after
that here you can see the another
organization. Right? This is the ID,
name, slug, description. Then we have
the members.
So this is the dummy data that we have
already added in the front end. Right?
Now to start this front end just open
this terminal and here we have to
install the dependencies. So simply
write npm
install.
It will install the packages
and uh just wait for it.
It is installing the package.
Now all the packages has been installed
and after that you will find a folder in
this client that is node_modules.
So it will create this folder and all
the packages will be added in this node
modules folder. After that we can run
our project. So just add npm
rundev
press enter.
So our project is running at this URL
localhost 5173. Let's open it in the web
browser. Copy this link and open in web
browser.
So you can see this is the front- end
template of project management.
Right? And in this one we have the dummy
data also.
And we can also change the theme. Right?
Now it is in the dark mode. Right? So
I'll just click here. So you can switch
to light mode or dark mode
like this.
After that let me show you all the
features of this template. So first we
have this dashboard and before this
dashboard area we have the navigation
bar also where you can switch the
workspace or organization.
Correct. And uh after that here we have
the
user icon in the right side which is not
functional yet because we have not added
the backend functionality. After that
here we have the search icon where you
can search for the project or task. Now
after this navbar here we have the
dashboard area where you can see the
overview like total number of projects
completed projects my task and overdue.
After that here you will find the active
projects. We have the project overview
right and you can see the status active
and we have the button called view all
that will take you to the projects page
where you can see all the projects right
now we are on the dashboard page so it
will display two projects here then we
have my task here also it is displaying
the task list and you can click here to
open the particular task and it is also
displaying the count here after that we
have the recent activity
then overdue in progress like this. Now
let's come here in this sidebar and
switch to different page. So I'll click
on this projects. So here you can see we
have two projects and we have this
search box. Then we have the filters.
Let me show you in light mode. Here we
have the filters.
I'll update the text color in the dark
mode also. And after that here you can
see this button
that is new project. So you can also
create a new project using this button
that will open a form like this where
you can add the project details and
create a new project in your workspace.
After that let's come here in this team.
So in this one you will get the list of
team members right and their role. After
that you can also search the team
members using this input field. And then
we have the other details like total
members, active projects and total task.
But with that we have more feature like
add members. So we will add the
functionality in this button add
members. Using that we can add new
members in this project.
And here you can see the button send
invitation. Right. So this is the team
page and after that we have the settings
in the left side. Here we'll add the
functionality to make the changes in the
organization settings. After that here
we have the task list. You can see we
can expand it and we'll see the list of
task. And if I click here it will open
this
discussion page where we can send the
messages also. Right? And in the right
side we have the task details and
project details. After that in the left
side you will find this projects right.
If I click on any project it will
display the tasks analytics calendar and
settings. Just click on this task. So it
will display all the tasks for the
particular project. And here we have
other stats like total task completed in
progress and team members.
We can switch the tab like this. If I
click on calendar here we have the
calendar then we have analytics then
settings. So in this settings page we
can make the changes in the project
details and here we have the option to
manage the members. Right. So this is
the front end only. We don't have the
functionality here. This is the static
template. Next we have to add the
features. We will make it functional. So
first we'll start with the user
authentication. For user authentication
feature we are going to use kirk. It is
most comprehensive user management
platform. It also provides organization
features that allow user to create
organization add user and invite user to
an organization.
Color also provides readytouse
components for user authentication and
organization management that we can
easily integrate in our ReactJS project.
So just click the link provided in the
description and sign up on the color
website. So I'll click on this button
and uh I'll sign up with my existing
Google account. I'll choose Google
After sign up, you will come to collect
dashboard where you need to create an
application. So I'll just click on this
button create application
and here we have to add the application
name. So I'll write project management
and after that you can enable the signup
methods. So I'll use Google signup and
email. You can also use other signup
methods like phone number, username,
Facebook, Apple, Microsoft. So I'll just
use Google signup and email and click on
create application button.
After that here we have the
documentation to set up the color in our
project. So I'll just click on this
react
and after that you can see the steps to
integrate the color authentication in
react project. So the first step is to
create and start the project using
weight and after that we need to install
the color for react using this command.
So just copy this one and come back to
the VS code.
So here we have this terminal and the
project is running. So just add Ctrl C
to stop the project and paste this
command. npm install at color/color
react.
So it is installing this package. So now
I'll see the next step. So the next step
is to add
file and in this env file we have to add
this
key. So let's create a environment
variable file. I'll just come back here
and in this client folder create a new
file and write the file name env.
Now in this one just paste this
environment variable just copy from here
and paste it here. So we have added this
color publicable key like this.
Now just come back and see the next
step. So the next step is to import the
pubable key in the main JSX or tsx file
and after that we have to use the color
provider tag in this same file. So let's
just copy this one
and come back to the VS code. And now
I'll open this
src then main dot jsx file. Now in this
one
you can see we have this create root. So
before that let me paste this code that
will import the pubable key and this if
statement.
After that just come back here
and you can see we have to import the
color provider tag. So just copy this
import statement paste it here
like this import color provider from
color/color
react. And after that we have to wrap
our application
using this color provider like this. So
let's just copy this one. I'll just copy
it and come here.
So
here you can see we have the browser
router and then we have this provider
right. So before this provider let's
paste this one that is color provider
then publishable key and after that we
have this app. So remove this app and
move this provider inside the color
provider. So now you can see the
structure.
First we have the browser router. Inside
this browser router we have the color
provider and after that we have this
provider. And in this one we have this
app.
Save the changes. Now we can use the
color components in any page or any
file. Right? So if I come back here in
this documentation you can see we can
use the
signed out component signin button. So
we can simply use these components to
use the color feature and create the
authentication pages and popup. So now
I'll just come back here
in the VS code and first we'll start the
project. So let's open the terminal and
write npm rundev.
So again the project is running on the
same URL and we can hide this terminal.
Now if I come back to the web browser
and you can see this dashboard is still
visible right so I'll just come back
here in the VS code and let me close
this file and after that let's open the
app dot jsx this is the first file
that will get executed right so in this
one you can see we have this home route
that is forward slash that's it so When
we open the homepage, it will open this
route. And here you can see we have
mounted the layout page. Correct? So in
this layout page, we have added the data
that will be displayed when we hit this
home route. So now let's open this
layout page. We will open this sidebar.
Come to pages. And here we have the
layout. Let's open layout.jsx file. Now
in this layout you can see we have this
div that is displayed on the web page.
So first we have the left sideb and
after that we have this div. In this div
we have the navigation bar and then we
have this outlet. In this outlet we can
display different pages. So this sidebar
and nav bar will be always displayed and
this outlet will display the child
pages.
Correct? But we have to hide this entire
div when the user is not logged in. For
that here we have to add one if
statement and we will check the user is
authenticated or not. For that
here we will import the color in this
page. So
let's add
import
curly braces. Let's add
use user.
Then we will import the
sign in
and uh from
and now let's provide the at color/color
react. So we have imported the use user
and signin component
right and after that let's get the user
from this use user.
So
here we'll write const
curly braces user and we will get this
user from the use user like this. Now
from this use user we will also get is
loaded. So just add comma is loaded like
this. After that you can see
so before this if statement that is
checking the loading a state here we
will add if
not of user
it means when the user is not logged in.
So in this case we will add return and
uh let's add this parenthesis here. And
we will provide a div
like this. And in this div we will add
the telewind classes. For that we'll
provide the class name property and
provide these tailwind classes.
Now in this div we have to display the
signin component. It means when the user
is not logged in then we have to display
the sign-in component. So let's add
sign in component. Save the changes.
After adding it, if I open the web page,
you can see on the same URL, we are
getting the sign-in component. Sign in
to project management. And here we have
the option to sign in using Google or we
can also sign in using email ID. And if
you are new on this website, you can
sign up using this link. Just click on
this sign up. So it will open the signup
page. You can see the signup component.
If I come back here, we have the sign-in
component. And if I refresh it, we
cannot see the dashboard. Now if I sign
in, let me sign in with my Google
account.
And after sign in or sign up, you can
access the
homepage or dashboard
like this.
After that you can see here we have this
icon called A. So instead of this icon
we will display the user icon from the
color account. For that let me just come
back here and we will open the
components. In this components you will
find navbar.jsx
file. Now in this navbar dot jsx let's
add import
curly braces. We will import the user
button. So we have the user button
component provided by color. So let's
add from
at color/color
react. Now let's mount this user button
in the navigation bar. So let's come
here. In the navbar we have this input
field. Then we have the right section.
In the right section we have this toggle
theme. Then we have the user button.
Right. So here you can see we have one
image. So just replace it. I'll put this
user button component.
That's it. Save the changes and open the
web page. Now you can see we have the
user profile icon in the top right
corner. If I switch to dark mode, you
can see this profile icon. If I click
here, here we have this
user name, email id, manage account and
sign out link.
And here if I click on this manage
account, you can update the profile
image, name, email. And here we have the
security option where you can delete
your account. So we have added the user
authentication in this project
management application. After that we
have to store this user data in the
database and for that we have to create
the back end also right so now we will
start creating the back end for that let
me just come back to the VS code and uh
I'll just close this file and come to
this sidebar and collapse this client
folder in this project manager folder or
project management folder we will create
a new folder so I'll create a new folder
with the name server. In this server
folder, we'll create the back end.
So in this server folder, we will create
the back end using express. So let's
right click on this server folder and
let's choose open in integrated
terminal. So now we have another
terminal and you can see the path. We
are in the server directory. Correct.
Here we'll add npm in it. But before
that we'll create a file also. So in
this server folder we'll create a new
file and write the file name that is
server.js.
So we have server.js file. And after
that in this terminal let's add npm
in it dash y. Press enter.
So it will create this package.json file
where you will find the name, version,
main, script, keywords, author, license
and description.
Let me open the package.json. So you can
see the details here. Right now in this
one we have to add the packages that we
will use to create our backend server.
Correct? So in this terminal
first we will add the
express because we'll create the back
end using express right. So let's add
npm
install and provide express. Then we'll
add next package that is course. Using
this we will allow the back end to
connect with any front end URL. After
that we'll add the
env so that we can use the environment
variables.
So we have added npm install express
course and
env. Now press enter. So it will install
these dependencies
in our backend project.
It is completed. After that we'll add
one more package. So just add npm
install
dash save dashdev and the package name
nodemon.
So this nodemon package will help us to
restart the backend server whenever we
will make any changes. It will
automatically restart the backend
server. And here we have added d-save
d-dev because we want to install this
package in dev dependencies only in the
development server only. So let's press
enter. So it will install this nodemon
also.
It is done. Now if I come here in this
package.json file you can see we have
all the dependencies like course.env and
express. And in this dev dependencies we
have the nodemon right after that here
we have the scripts
right. So in this one let's add comma
and here we'll add double quote and
provide the server. So we are writing
the script name server and here let's
add double quote again and in this one
we will add nodemon space server.js that
is the main file. So whenever we will
start our project using this server
script it will use this nodemon
server.js that will automatically
restart the back end whenever we will
make any changes. Now here we'll add one
more property. So here we have the name
version and main. So after that just add
double quote and provide type. So in
this type let's add module like this. So
when we use this type module, we can use
the import statement in our project.
After adding this script, let me just
close this and open the main file that
is server.js file. And in this one, we
will create a basic express app. So
let's add import express from the
express package. And after that, let's
import the env/config.
After that we'll import the course also.
We have already added this
package. Correct? Now using this express
we'll create one app. So let's add con
app equal to
express like this. And after that in
this one we'll add the middleware. So
let's add app dot use and provide the
express
dot JSON. So all the request will be
passed using this JSON method. After
that again add app dot use and here
let's add the course.
So it will parse all the request using
this course. After that we have to
create the first route. So I'll write
app dot get method here we'll add the
path slash this is the home route and
then we'll add the add a function. So
when we hit this route it will execute
this function in this function parameter
we will get the request and response
like this and after that it will return
the response.
So just at response dot send and here we
will send the message. So the message is
server is live like this and uh after
that we have to add a port number where
we will start our backend server. So
let's add const port equal to process
dot env dot port. So if the port is
available in the environment variable it
will be used. else we will start this on
port number 5,000. After that we have to
start the
application that is express app. So here
let's add app dot listen. Using this
listen we can start the application. So
first we have to provide the port that
will be 5,000 and after that we have to
add one function that will get executed.
So here let's add console log and uh in
this one we'll add the message. So let's
add the back tick server running on port
and then we'll add dollar sign curly
braces to insert the template lit. So
just add the port here
like this. So what is happening here?
First we have created the app using this
express package. Now in this one we have
added this JSON method and course method
to parse all the request. After that we
have created a route that is the home
route using this path slash using this
get method. So when we will hit this
path then we will see this message
server is live. It will send this
response. Now to run this application we
need a port number. So here we have
defined the port number and after that
we have used this listen method. So we
have this app dot listen that will start
the application and in this one we have
to provide the port number and then we
have to provide the function that will
get executed. So when this function will
get executed it will display the message
in the terminal because we have added
console log. So it will display the
message in the VS code terminal that is
server running on port 5,000. Now let's
save the changes and start the project.
So to start this backend project or
backend server again open the terminal
and uh in this terminal you can see we
are in this server directory right. So
here let's add npm
run server. We have added this server a
script right that will start the server
using nodemon. Let's press enter. And
after that you can see the message
it is starting the project using this
nodemon starting node server.js and then
we have the console log called server
running on port 5000. So the backend
server is successfully running. You can
also verify this backend server by
opening the URL in the web browser. So
if I open the web browser and in the new
tab let's add local host
col 5,000.
So here you can see this message server
is live. So it means the backend server
is successfully running. We have
successfully created a simple express
app.
After creating the simple express app,
now we will add the color o in this back
end. So I'll just come back to the web
browser and open color homepage. Then
let's open the documentation. We'll
click on go to docs.
And after that scroll down you will find
this
express right. So just click on this
express
and here we have the steps to integrate
the color in the express back end. So
you can see the command npm install at
color/express.
Just copy this one and come back to the
VS code. Open the terminal and stop this
project using ctrl c
and paste this command. Press enter. it
will install the color in the back end.
After that, let's see the next command.
So, next we have to add the keys in the
environment variable. So, first we have
to create env file. If I come back here,
open the sidebar. We have the server
folder. In this server folder, create a
new file and write the file name. Env.
Now in this one just provide these
environment variables. So click on this
icon to copy it and paste it here. So we
have provided color pubable key and
color secret key. Then come back here
and we need to install env. We have
already added it. After that we can use
this color middleware in the main file.
So first we have to import it. import
color middleware from color/express.
Just copy this import statement, open
the server.js file and add it here. So
we have imported the color middleware
and after that we have to add it as the
middleware in the app. So
after this course let's add app dot use
and in this one simply add color
middleware and call it like this. So we
have added the color integration in the
back end. After that we'll come back
here and you can see
we can use this required o to protect
any route. Let's skip this and this is
optional. So let's close it. So we have
added the color o in the back end. Now
we have to connect our backend project
with the database. To store our data we
are going to use neon database. Neon is
a fully managed serverless postgress
database built for modern application.
Neon helps developers to build a
scalable and reliable application
faster. It comes with powerful feature
like branching and autoscaling that
simplifies the development and
management. With Neon free plan, you can
create up to 20 projects and store up to
500 MB of data at no cost. So just click
on the link given in the description and
sign up on Neon for free. So I'll just
click on this sign up button
and I will sign in using my Google
account.
After sign up, you need to provide the
organization name and create the
organization. Then you need to create a
project. So let me add the project name
here. All right.
Project management.
Then you can choose the nearest region
and after that click on create button.
So it will create a project and after
that let's see the document how to
connect this neon database with your
project. So I'll open the homepage
then go to docs
and uh in this top navigation bar you
will find this develop and here we have
OMS just click here
and after that we will choose this
Prisma we will use Prisma to connect the
database.
So after opening this link you can see
the steps to connect the database with
the project. So first step is to connect
to neon from Prisma. So here we need to
get the key right. You can see we have
to get the key from the neon dashboard
and after that we have to create the
schema.prisma Prisma file and provide
this configuration and after that we
have to add the database URL in the env
file right and uh after that this
database URL will be like this and uh
let's scroll down
and you will find this
configuration for a schema.prisma Prisma
scroll down and in the environment
variable you need to provide two URLs
that will be database URL and direct URL
right so let me start with the
environment variable only I'll just copy
this environment variables and come here
in the VS code open env file and here
let's paste it and remove this dummy URL
so first we have the
database URL and then we have the direct
URL correct after that to get this URL
I'll just come back and open neon
console or
dashboard then click on this connect
button
and here you will find this connection
string right let's just click here and
copy this a string
copy this and paste it in this database
URL
within this double quote.
After that, I'll just come back here and
you can see this connection pulling is
on. So, turn it off using this toggle
button and after that again copy this
string that is the connection string.
Copy this one and we can paste it here
in this direct URL. So we have added the
database URL and direct URL in the
environment variable. After that I'll
just come back here. Let me just close
it and see the document.
So what we have to do we have to create
schema doprisma file and add this
configuration in that. And uh after that
you can see we have to add this command
npx prisma generate.
Then we have to install the Prisma using
this command. npm install WS then Prisma
adapter neon then neon database
serverless. Right? So
let me add it one by one. So first we'll
start with this Prisma schema or a
schema.prisma file. So in this a
schema.prisma file we will also add the
schema to create the table. Right. So we
have already provided the schema in the
asset file or asset folder. If I come
back here in the project we have the
client then src assets and in this
assets you will find the schema.prisma
file. Right. Let me just copy this
schema.prisma Prisma
and come back here in the back end.
Here we have the server. In this server,
we will create a folder. So in this
server folder, we have to create a new
folder. So I'll write the folder name
that is Prisma.
And in this Prisma folder
just paste this schema.prisma
right and after adding it again come
back to the VS code. Now in this server
folder you can see we have the Prisma
folder and in this Prisma folder we have
a schema.prisma.
Now if I open it you can see here we
have this configuration that you can see
in that document. Right?
And after that we have the
enums here. Let's scroll down. Here we
have the model to store the user data.
Right? So we will create the user table
where we will add the ID, name, email,
image, created at, updated ad. Then
we'll add the other properties like
workspaces, projects, task, comments,
owned workspaces and project member. And
in this one we will link other tables.
So here we have added the relations with
other table. So this is the model to
create the user table where we will
store the user data. Similarly, we have
added the model for workspace,
workspace member,
project,
project member, task,
comment.
So, it is already added here. You can
find it in the asset file or asset
folder. After that, let's see the next
step. So you can see the next step here
that is npx prisma generate. Just copy
this one and come here.
Open the terminal. In the backend
terminal just add this npx prisma
generate. Press enter.
Now press yes or y.
It is executing this command. So I'll
copy the next one also. So here we have
the second command. Just copy this one
and come back here.
So just wait for this previous command
to be completed.
Now it has been completed. Now let's
paste the new command that we have just
copied. Just paste it here and press
enter. That will install WS websocket.
Then Prisma adapter
and neon serverless. It has been
installed. After that, let's see the
next step. So the next step is to create
this config file.
Right? But before creating that, I'll
just come back here and first copy this
npx prisma generate. We have to add it
in the package.json. So I'll open
package.json file in the back end. And
here you can see the
a script, right? So let me remove this
test script from here. So first we have
the a start and then server. So in this
a start
I'll write
a space
prisma
generate
then and operator like this. So it will
execute this prisma generate and node
server.js JS for the
online deployment. Right? And here we'll
add one more script. So just add double
quote and write post install.
And after that in this one just provide
this one npx prisma generate like this.
So we have added this npx prisma
generate here.
So whenever we will deploy this project
online and that will start the project
using this start command or a start a
script it will execute this command also
and this one also and after installation
it will also execute this one. That's
it. Now let's create the configuration
file here. So in this server we'll
create a folder called config.
We have created the config folder right
now. In this config folder, we'll create
a file. So write the file name
prisma.js.
We have created the prisma.js file and
come back here. So you can see the code
here. Let me just copy this one. Click
here to copy this entire code, right?
And paste it here. So in this one we
have provided importenv.
Then we have imported the Prisma client,
Prisma neon and neon config from this
package. Right? And after that we have
imported the WS that is websocket
and uh after that
here we have this connection string. So
the connection string is imported from
the environment variable using this
process envatabase
URL correct. Then we have this adapter
using this new Prisma neon. And in this
one the connection string is already
provided.
After that we have this Prisma equal to
global.prisma.
And here we have added all operator new
Prisma client adapter.
Correct. After that we have the if
statement. In this if statement we have
added this
node environment equal to development.
And we have to provide the node
environment in the env file also. Right?
So I'll just copy this one node env
file. And here at the top
let me provide
node env that is environment equal to
and here let's set development.
So when you will upload this project
online just change this development to
production. That's it. After that let's
come here. So this is the configuration
file for Prisma. And after that let's
see the next step.
So we have successfully configured the
connection with the neon database using
Prisma and we have already added the
schema also right next we have to create
the table in our database using these
schema. For that let's open the terminal
again. In this terminal we will add npx
prisma db push like this. Just add this
command npx prism db push. Press enter.
Once you will execute this command, it
will create the tables in the neon
database according to our schema.
So this command has been executed. After
that I'll open the web browser and let
me just come back to the neon console
and after that let's click on this
tables. So here you can see we have all
the tables that we have defined in the
schema file. So we have the comment
project
member then task user workspace and
workspace member. So we have multiple
tables here. If I open anyone like user
so you can see we don't have any data in
this user table. So what we have to do
next? We have to get the user data from
the color because in this project you
can see we have added the user
authentication using color right. So the
color will provide the user data using
behooks. So next we have to configure
the color behind
manage the color behooks scheduling and
background jobs we are going to use
inest. It provides multiple feature to
manage the background jobs, schedulings
and chron jobs. So just click on the
link given in the description to sign up
on inest platform. So I'll just click on
this button sign up and
I will continue with my Google account.
I'll click on this Google icon.
After sign up, you need to create an
organization. So I'll write the name
here that is project management.
After adding the project name, you need
to add the image. So let me add one
image here and click on create
organization.
Let's click on escape button. So we have
created the ingest account. Now let's
authenticate this inest account with the
color web hook setup. Right? So let's
come back here in this collect dashboard
go to configure scroll down and here you
will find this bebooks just click here
and on this baybooks page you will find
this button add endpoint let me just
click here
and after that click on this drop-down.
So in this drop-down you will get this
ingest option. Just click on this ingest
and click on connect to ingest.
After that click on approve
and after that you need to scroll down
and click on this create button.
Now it is created and after that you
will get this signing secret here. Let
me click here.
So this is the behook secret key. You
need to add this key in the environment
variable. So just come back to the VS
code
and open env file. And in this one here
we have color publishable key and secret
key. So after this secret key let's add
this color behook secret equal to and
after that just copy the beu secret key
from here. Just copy this one
and paste it here.
That's it. And after that, let me just
come back here in the
ingest and we will open this key. Click
on this key icon. Then click on event
keys. So I'll click here. So here you
will find the ingest
event keys right. So you need to add it
in the environment variable. So first
come back here in the env file. Scroll
down and here let's add inest event key
and then we will paste the ingest
signing key
like this. So we have added two
environment variables and after that
just copy the key from here. Copy this
one that is event key. Paste it here.
And after that come back and uh click on
this key icon again and choose this
signin key. Click here
and uh after that let's click on this
icon to copy this signin key. Let's copy
and paste it here.
So we have provided the ingest event key
and signin key. After that let's come
back here and uh we will open the
documentation here. So click on this
integrations
or we can also go to ingest homepage
and click on docs
and uh after that
in this one I'll click on this nodejs
and here you will find this express js.
So we are using the express js to create
our back end. Now let's scroll down and
see the first step. So first we have to
install the ingest package using this
command. Just copy this one. Come back
here and open the terminal. Now in this
terminal let me add this command. npm
install ingest. Press enter.
After that let me see the next step. We
have to start the dev server. We can
skip this one. And after that you can
see create and ingest client. So we have
to create the
index.js or ts file in the ingest
folder. So first we'll create this
ingest folder in the back end. Right? So
just come back here and it is executing
this command and we can create the
folder here. In this server folder we'll
create the new folder. So let's add the
folder name inest. So we have added the
ingest folder in the server. And after
that in this one we have to add the file
name index dot js. So let's create a
file called index.js
like this.
And after that in this one we have to
add the import a statement importing
inest from the ingest. So let's copy
this one or let me just copy everything
from this code. copy it and paste it
here
in this index.js file. So we have added
importing inest from the ingest package
and after that create a client to send
and receive events and then we have
created the function array and in this
one we will pass all the ingest
functions.
After that let's come here in this
terminal. This
command has been executed. So we can
start the project using npm rundev
or npm run server because it is the
backend server.
Press enter. So it will start the
project on port 5000. Now just hide this
terminal. And after that let's come here
and see the next step. So the next step
is to setting the end point that is the
HTTP endpoint. For that we have to use
this app dot use/ API/est
and serve client inest and functions.
Right? So we have to add this statement.
Let me just copy this one and we will
come back to the VS code. And in this
one let's open the server.js file. And
here
after this first route let me add a
space and provide this app dot
use/ingest
comma serve then client inest and
functions. Now we have to import this
serve. Let me just come back here. You
can see here we have to import this
serve and this inest and function also.
So let's copy this one and paste it
here. So we have added this import
statement also. Now it is correct. Save
the changes. Here you can see the path
is starting from src. Right? So let me
update the path here. We'll write dot
/est
folder/
index.js
file because in this file we have
created the
inest app and functions array. You can
see in this file we have the
ingest and this functions right and it
is imported here in the server.js.
Now let's see the next step in this
ingest documentation. So after setting
the HTTP endpoint you can see the next
step is to write the ingest function
right and here is the format to create
the ingest function. We'll use ingest
do.create function method. In this one
we have to provide the id and event name
and after that we'll add the
asynchronous add function where we'll
get the parameter called event and step
and after that we'll execute our code
here in this function. Right. So we have
to create the ingest functions to handle
different background jobs. So we will
handle the user creation, deletion and
updation using this ingest function and
later we'll create other inest functions
also. So for now we need the user data
right. So I'll just come back here
and let's open index.js file and uh
before this function here we will create
different injest functions and first let
me update the id. So instead of this my
id here we'll write project management
right and after that here we'll add the
comment that is ingest function to save
user data to a database. So let's create
a function. I'll write conster
creation equal to
ingest dot
create function
and after that let's add the object here
and in this object we'll add the ID. So
in this id let's add any ID in a string
format. So I'll write sync user from
color
right and after that we'll add comma and
add another object. Here we'll add the
event. So I'll write the event name that
is color/ user.created.
After that we'll add comma and here
we'll create the asynchronous add a
function
and in this function parameter we will
only get the event and after that here
let's get the data from this event. So
I'll write con curly braces data equal
to event
then let's add await and here we will
use the prisma to store this data in the
database. So let's add
Prisma and import it from the config
folder Prisma file. It has been imported
as you can see here. Right? And in this
one we'll add the file name extension
also.js
like this. So here in this Prisma we'll
add dot
user for user table. Then we'll add dot
create method.
And here we have to add the data. So
let's add the data property and provide
the object. Now in this object we have
to provide the id. So the id will be
data do id. After that we'll add comma
provide the email. In this email let's
provide the data dot
email
addresses. So I'll write email addresses
index zero. Then we'll add question mark
if it is available then dot let's add
email address.
And here also we'll add the question
mark like this. If the data is available
then we'll find the email addresses
array. And from that one we'll get the
first element using this index zero. And
from there we'll get the email address.
Add the comma here. And after that let's
add the name property. We will store the
name.
And in this one let's add the
data question mark dot first name plus
we'll add the space here
and then plus and provide the data
question mark dot last name. So we will
store the first and last name in the
name property. After that we'll add the
image here. In this image property,
let's add data question mark then dot
image URL. So it will give the image URL
from color. So we have created one inest
function using that we can store the
user data in the database using the
Prisma. Right? And after that we'll
create the another function using that
we can delete the user data. Right?
So here we'll add comment
inest function to delete user from
database. So again let's add the same
function here. I'll just copy this one
paste it here. In this one we'll change
the name. So the function name will be
sync user deletion equal to inest dot
create function. Then we will change the
ID. So the ID will be
delete user with color. After that we
will update the event name. So the event
will be
clerk user dodeleted.
After that here also we'll add the async
function with the event and from this
event we'll get the data and after that
using this data we have to delete the
user data from the database. So just add
await prisma do user dot delete method.
Right. And here let's remove this one.
Simply add where
and after that let's provide the id and
in this id let's add the data dot id
that's it so it will get deleted from
the database after that we have to add
the ingest function to update the user
data right so again copy this one but
before that we'll write the comment so
here we'll write the comment
inest function
to update user data in database and let
me just copy the first function that is
for creating the user data. I'll just
copy and paste it here. In this one,
let's add the function name that is sync
user updation. After that, we'll add the
ID here. So the ID is
update user from color. Then we will
update the event name. So the event name
is color/ user.updated.
After that here you can see we are
getting the data from the event and then
we have added await prisma dot user dot
and provide the update method right and
uh after that here let me add where
it will be one object and add the comma
here now in this where first we have to
add the id. So let's add the id and the
id will be data do id. So it will choose
the data to be updated. And after that
here we have the data property. From
this one remove the id. Here we have
provided the email name and image.
That's it. So it will update the user
data in the database.
After creating these inest functions, we
have to export it using this functions
array. Right? So in this functions array
let me add all the functions one by one.
So first we have this sync user
creation. Let's add it here.
Then add comma or let me add it in the
new line like this. So the first
function is sync user creation. Then the
second function is sync user deletion.
then comma and provide the next one that
is
sync user updation.
That's it. So we have created three
functions only and after that we have to
deploy this project online.
So before deployment we have to add some
configuration in this project. For that
let's
come here in this project management
folder that is the project folder. Here
we have to create a file. So we'll
create a new file here and write the
file name dot get ignore.
In this file
let's add node
modules. So it will ignore this folder.
And with that we'll also add env. So it
will ignore this environment variable
file. After that we'll add some other
configuration also. So I'll just open
the web browser and here simply open
github.com/greatest
stackdev. Open the github profile. Here
you will find this nodes. In this one
you will find versaljson config form.
Let's open it. And after that you can
see here we have versel.json. JSON
configuration for the express back end
and for the front end right in the front
end you have added the router then you
need to add it right so let's create
this file here in this server folder
we'll create a file called versaljson
and we'll create the same file in this
client so create a new file in the
client that is versel dojson
like this Now just come back here. Copy
this a small code script for the client.
Just copy and paste it here.
So we have added this code in the
versel.json file in the client folder or
client project. Now close it. And after
that let's just copy this code and paste
it in the versel.json file for the back
end that is the server. So let's paste
it here and save the changes. Close it.
Now we have to upload this code on
GitHub. So just click on this source
control icon. Click on initialize
repository.
So here you will find this number of
files that is 56. Here we'll add the
message
first commit. Click on commit button.
Then click on publish branch.
And here you can change the repository
name also and choose the repository type
like private or public. So I'll choose
this private GitHub repository and the
project name is project management.
Let's click here. So it will upload the
code in the GitHub profile.
So it has been uploaded. Now let me open
my GitHub page.
So here you can see this project has
been uploaded on this GitHub repository.
This is the client folder. This is the
server folder. Right? Next we have to
deploy this server or back end. Right?
For deployment we are going to use
Versel. So let's open versel.com and you
need to create an account here. Then
come to dashboard and after that click
on this button add new and choose
project. So create a new project here.
And after that here you will find the
list of repositories available in your
GitHub account. So I'll click on this
import button in front of this project
management. Click on import. And after
that here you need to choose the root
directory. So click on this edit and
choose server because we are deploying
the back end only. Right? So we have
selected server. Then click on continue.
And after that here you can add the
project name. So let me write project
mgt
that is project management server like
this. Then we have to add the
environment variables here. So I'll
expand this one and here we will paste
the environment variables. So I'll just
come back here and open the
server folder env file and copy all the
environment variables from here. Just
copy and paste it here.
Now in this one you can see we have
added node env development. So instead
of development here we will write
production
just updated this and after that let's
click on this button deploy.
So it is deploying our backend server.
You can see the status here.
Now it is successfully deployed. You can
see server is live. Let's click on
continue to dashboard. And after that
you will find the domain here. Let me
just click on this domains.
So here we have the live link of our
backend server.
It is opening.
So you can see the server is live and
let me just copy this backend URL. And
now we have to add this URL in the inest
app. So let's come back here.
and come to
ingest dashboard.
In this inest dashboard just click on
this get started button or click on this
sync new app button and after that here
you need to provide the URL right so
I'll just
provide the backend URL here and then
write /
API/ingest.
If I come back to the VS code
in the main file, you will find this
path. You can see we have added the HTTP
endpoint that is / API/est.
Right? That's why we are adding it here.
This is the base URL of our backend
server. Then / API/est.
Then click on sync app.
Now you can see synced app. And after
sync you will find all your functions
here. So till now we have created three
inest function right that is sync user
from clerk delete user from clerk update
user from clerk it is added here. So we
have successfully configured the color
web hooks using ingest and after that if
I create any new account then the user
data will get saved in the database. So
now let's try it. I'll just come back
here in the project and here let's come
to this manage account. I'll delete this
account.
I'll click on this button delete.
After that it is asking for the OTP
because it is the sensitive task. So we
have added the OTP here and deleted this
account.
So now the account has been deleted. And
after that you can see once we are
logged out we cannot access this
dashboard. It is protected. And if I
click on continue with Google we can
create an account here. So I'll create a
new account using the same email ID and
click on continue.
And after that we can see the dashboard.
So you can see we have created the
account on this page and we can see the
dashboard. Now let me open our neon
database. I'll come here and uh here
we'll come to this user table.
Let's click on this refresh button.
Here we don't have the user data right.
So let me just come here in the ingest
and come to this runs.
So you can see it is running
that is user deleted user created. Let
me expand it
and uh
I'll scroll down.
Let me click here. And here we are
getting some error in this user creation
invalid. Prisma do user do.create.
If I scroll down here, you can see email
is missing, right? Argument email is
missing. So, let me just fix it. I'll
just come back here. And in this index
js file, you can see we have added email
property. In this one, we have added
email addresses index zero and then we
have dot email address. So, here we have
missed one s. Let me just correct this
spelling. Email address. That's it. Save
the changes. And after that let's try to
create an account again. So I'll just
come here
in the matrix runs and it is failed
right. So I'll just come here and delete
the account again. So click on manage
account security delete and write the
text delete account
and we have made the changes. So we have
to update the code, right? And then we
have to deploy the project again. So
I'll just come back here and click on
this
source control icon. And here we'll add
the message
fixed
user creation
commit.
Okay.
So it will update the code in GitHub. So
let's open the GitHub profile. Let me
refresh it.
So it is updated just now. And after
that it will also redeploy the back end.
So I'll come to deployments.
So you can see it is again redeploying
the project. Right now it is ready. So
the project has been redeployed. After
that we can try to create a new account.
So I'll click on this continue with
Google
and here we have created one account.
So after creation it will redirect to
dashboard. Now again come here in the
database
and click on this refresh.
Now you can see here we are getting the
user data. So when we create the account
the user data is getting saved in the
database. So here we have the user ID
name email then image URL and then we
have the created at property and other
details. So if I open the ingest
dashboard let me refresh it.
So now you will find
the new event here and it is completed
right? You can see the name user doc
created. Let me open it. You can see it
is completed successfully.
So this ingest function is working fine.
So till now in our project we have added
the user authentication and after that
we have connected the database to store
the data and we have connected the
ingest and created the inest functions
to manage the background jobs and using
that we will store the user data in the
database.
Now we have to add the functionality to
create the workspace or organization.
In this workspace, admin can add a new
users and they can also add the project.
Inside the project, we can add the task
and we can assign the task to any user.
To enable the organization
functionality, we are going to use
color. So let's open color dashboard and
in this dashboard we will come to
configure option and in the left side
you will find the organization
management. Just click on this settings
and after that you will find this button
enable organizations.
Let's click here.
Click on enable
and uh we can also enable this checkbox.
Click enable.
Now here you can see in this
organization we can add up to five
members in the free plan. And here we
have the allow personal accounts. You
need to enable it. Now in this one
scroll down and here you will find this
enable organization slug. You need to
enable this one also so that the
organization will have the unique
identifier. After that let's scroll down
and uh
here you can see allow new members to
delete organizations. So let me uncheck
this one or disable this. So the new
member cannot delete the organization.
After that click on the save button.
Now it is saved. So we have enabled the
organization functionality from the
color dashboard.
And whenever we will create the
organization or we will add a new member
or we will update the organization then
we will get the data in the color web
hooks and whenever we will create the
organization and update the organization
we have to update the data in our
database also. So first we will receive
the data from the web hooks and then we
will store it in the database. For that
let me just come back here in the VS
code and in this one that is index.js
file inside this ingest here we'll
create the ingest functions that will
manage the color web hooks for
organization.
So here we'll create some
ingest functions to manage the color web
hooks. So let me add the comment here.
All right. Ingest function to save
workspace data to a database.
Right. And let's create the function
here. So I'll write const
sync workspace creation equal to
inest dot create function method.
And after that let's add the object. And
here we have to add one ID. So I'll
write the id sync workspace from color.
After that add the comma and add another
object. Here we will add the event name.
So let's add event
color/organization.created.
So from this color web hooks we will get
this event organization dot created
like this. So whenever this event
occurred then we have to execute a
function. So let's add
a sync add function
and in this function parameter we will
get that event. So let's dstructure that
event here and after that in this
function we will get the data from this
event. So I'll write const curly braces
data
equal to event
right. So we are getting this event from
the color web hooks and in that event we
will get the data right and after that
we have to store this data in the
database. For that let's add await then
Prisma dot and here we will use the
workspace table. Let's add workspace. If
I come back to web browser and open the
neon database here you can see we have
created the workspace
table right and let's use that here. So
here we have added workspace dot
create method and uh in this one we'll
add the object. First we have to add the
data and in this data let's add the
object where we will add the id. So the
id is data dot id. After that we'll add
the name property. In this name we will
add the data dot name.
Then add the comma and provide slug.
And let's add the data dot slug.
After that we will add the
owner id. In this owner id let's provide
the data dot
created by.
Then we will add comma and here we'll
add the next property
image URL. And in this image URL let's
add the data dot image URL
like this. So these workspace data will
get saved in the neon database. After
that in this workspace or organization
we have to add the admin. Right?
So here let's add comment and we'll add
the text called add creator as admin
member.
Now let's add await
prisma
dot workspace member.
Then we'll add dot
create method. And here we'll add the
object and provide the data. And let's
add the user ID. In this user ID, we
have to provide the data that we are
getting from the event. So let's add the
data here
dot created by.
And let me update this one also. It will
be user ID like this.
Then we'll add one more property here
that is workspace ID.
And in this workspace id let's add this
one data do id
after that here we have to provide the
role so I'll write role it will be admin
that's it so we have added the workspace
data in the database and we have also
added the admin role in the database for
this workspace.
After that we have to create another
ingest function using that we can update
the data in the database whenever we
update the organization or workspace.
So let's add the comment here that is
inest function to update workspace data
in database. So here let's add a new
function. I'll write the function name
const sync workspace updation equal to
inest dot create function and in this
one let's add first object where we have
to add the id. So the id is
update workspace from color. Then we
have to add the event here. So let's add
curly braces. it will be event
color/organization.updated.
So whenever this organization dot
updated event occurred in the color
paybox then we have to update the data
in the database also. So we'll create
the asynchronous arrow function and
dstructure the event in this parameter.
Now from this event we can get the data.
So let's add
const curly braces data equal to event.
Next we have to update the data in
database. So let's add await
prisma dot workspace
dot update method.
And here we have to provide where
and let's add the id and provide the
data dot id. So this will be the
workspace ID where we have to update the
data. Then add the comma and we'll add
the data property
and here let's add the name.
So I'll just copy from here name slug
and image URL. I'll just copy it here.
Remove this owner ID. It cannot be
updated. So we can update the name, slug
and image URL. That's it. So we have
added the ingest function to update the
organization.
Next we have to add the ingest function.
Using that we can delete an
organization.
So here again add the comment
inest function to delete workspace from
database. So whenever the workspace or
organization gets deleted we have to
delete it from the database. So I'll
write const and the function name sync
workspace deletion equal to
inest dot create function
and uh in this
function we will add ID. So let's add
the object ID. It will be delete
workspace with color. Right.
Let's remove this curly braces from
here.
And uh after that here we have to add
the event. So I'll write object and the
property name is event and the event
name is color/organization.deed.
So whenever we get this event
color/organization
dodeleted in the color box in that case
we have to delete the data from
database. So let's add
a sync arrow function. Then we will
dstructure the event in this parameter
and uh after that here we'll add the
data. So let's add con data
from event. After that we have to add a
weight and we will use Prisma
dot workspace.
Then we'll add dot delete
and in this delete just add where in
this where property simply provide the
id. So the id will be the data dot id.
So it will delete the particular
workspace data from the neon database.
Next we have to add one more inest
function. Using that we can update the
new member in the workspace in our
database. So
here let's add a space and we will add
the comment. So I'll write the comment
here. ingest function to save workspace
member data to a database.
So I'll write a new function here. So
just add const
sync workspace member creation equal to
inest dot create function and here let's
add the object. First we have to define
the id. So the id is sync workspace
member from color. Then add comma and
object. In this object we will add the
event. So let's add the event name that
is color/organization
invitation dot accepted.
So whenever the new member invitation is
accepted it means a new member is added
in the workspace.
So after that we have to update our
database also. So let's add the function
here async arrow function and get the
event in this function.
Now from this event let's get the data.
So let's just copy and paste it here.
Now we have the data and after that
let's add a weight
prisma dot workspace member. You can see
in this neon database we have this
workspace member right. So we have added
prisma dotworkspace member
dot create and uh here
let's add the data and then we'll add
user id.
In this user id simply add the data dot
Then we will add the next property that
is workspace id. And uh in this
workspace id let's add the data
dot organization
id
then comma and here we'll add the role.
In this role, let's add the data. In
this data, we will get the role name. So
just add rod name.
And uh after that we have to convert it
into a string. So I'll just remove it.
And first we'll write a string here. And
in this a string provide data dot roll
name. And after that we have to convert
this a string into uppercase. So let's
add two uppercase.
That's it.
So here we have added another function
using that we can update the new user in
the organization in our database. So we
have created four new ingest function.
Right now we have to export all these
inest function using this functions
array. So here let's add comma and
provide the function name that is sync
workspace creation. After that we will
add
sync workspace
updation. After that we will add sync
workspace deletion. And then we'll add
sync workspace
member creation. So we have added all
four new inest functions and exported it
using this functions array. Right. After
creating all these inest functions, next
we have to sync our inest application.
But before that we have to deploy the
changes. So just click on this source
control icon
and here we'll add the commit inest
functions added for workspace. Click on
commit
sync changes. So it will upload the code
on GitHub and it will also redeploy our
versel back end. So let's come back here
in this versel dashboard. Come to
deployments
and you can see it is again deploying
the project. You can see the status here
building.
So once it is ready we can sync our
inest application. So we will just wait
for few seconds. Now you can see it is
ready. It is redeployed again. Right.
And after that let's come back here in
this ingest dashboard. And uh right now
you can see we have only three functions
right that is for the user creation,
deletion and updation right now let me
click here
and after that click on this reync
button
and click on reync app. Now you can see
here we have total seven functions right
you can see the functions name that is
user function user delete update and
creation and then we have the workspace
function also delete workspace then
update workspace then
sync workspace it means creating a new
workspace and here we have the sync
workspace member it means adding a
member in the workspace. So we have
total seven inest functions. So we will
manage the web hooks to update the
user data and workspace data in the
database.
Now after that let's create some
controller function so that we can get
the workspace data. So I'll just come
back to the VS code.
Now in this one
here we have the server folder. So in
this server folder we'll create a new
folder and write the folder name
controllers.
In this controllers folder we will
create the controller file for
workspace. So create a new file and
write the file name workspace
controllers.
We will add workspace controller.js.
Now in this one let's add the comment
all right
get all workspaces for user. So here we
have to create a function that will
return all the workspace of particular
user. So let's add export
const and the function name. So I'll
write the function name get
user workspace or workspaces
equal to asynchronous arrow function and
in the function parameter we will get
request and response.
Now here first we will add the try catch
statement. Now in this try block we have
to get the user ID and uh this user id
will be provided using the request do.
So let's add const
curly braces
user id equal to await then we'll add
request dot
o.
So now we have the user ID and for this
user id we have to find the list of
workspaces.
To find the workspace here let's add
const
workspaces
equal to await. Then we will use prisma
and import the prisma from config
folder. It has been imported. Write the
file name extension js.
After that just add Prisma dot
workspace
dot
find many
and here let's add the object provide
where in this fair property let's add
the members
and in this members let's add
sum and uh here we'll add the user ID
And this user id will be the user ID
that we are getting from the request do
function.
After that we'll add comma and here
let's add include
in this include property. Let's add the
members property.
And uh here we will provide
include
user
and it will be true.
After that
here we have to add the projects also.
So let's add projects
and uh in this projects I'll write
include
and here we'll add the task property. So
just add task
and uh in this task I'll add include
and provide the
assigne true.
Then we'll provide the comments property
here.
And in this comments property, let's add
include.
And uh here we'll add user true.
After this task here we'll provide the
members.
In this members just add include
user true. That's it.
And uh after that here we'll add
comma
owner property and let's make it true
and uh after that here simply add
response
dot JSON
and uh simply provide this workspaces.
So in this response we will return the
workspaces.
After that
let's come to the catch block. If any
error occurs in the try block then catch
block will be executed. So here we will
display the message in console. So just
add console log and provide this error.
After that we will send the response
also. So just add response dot
a status.
And in the status let's add the code
500.
Then we'll add dot JSON
and uh here we will add the message. So
I'll write message property. It will be
error doc code or error dossage.
That's it. So here we have created the
controller function. Using that we can
get the workspaces for a particular
user. Right? Now we'll add one more
controller function. So here we'll add
the comment first that is add member to
workspace and here let's create the
function with the name add member. So
just add export const add member equal
to asynchronous addo function and in the
function parameter let's get the request
and response. After that add the try
catch a statement and in this catch
block again we'll add the same code. So
just copy this one and paste it here. We
have added console log error and
response dot status 500 and then JSON
message property and the message
property will be either error docode or
error dot message.
Now come to this try block. Now in this
try block again we need the user ID. So
I'll just copy this statement and paste
it here. So first we'll get the user id
from the request dot o function. After
that let's add const email ro workspace
id and message. Let's get all these data
from request dot body because we are
adding the user right. So for adding the
user we need the email role workspace ID
and the message.
Now after that let's add the comment
here that is check if user exist. So
I'll write const
user equal to await and here we will use
prisma dot user table dot find unique
and after that let's add the where
property
and provide the email. So we have
provided the email so that we will get
to know that user exist or not. So here
we'll add the if statement and write not
of user. Suppose the user does not exist
with this email id. So in this case we
will return the response. So just add
return response do a status and provide
4.4.
then dot JSON method and here we'll add
the message that is user not found.
Now suppose the user is available. So
here we will check for the
workspace and role. So let's add the if
statement
if not of workspace ID or
not of role. So if we are not getting
the workspace ID or ro data in the
request body. So in that case we cannot
add the user. Right? So here also we'll
add this statement
return response do a status 400
and then we'll add the JSON and provide
the message that is missing required
parameters.
Now suppose the user is available,
workspace ID is available, role is also
available. After that here we'll add
another if statement. if
not of
and then we'll add the array and in this
one we'll add the admin and member.
There are two elements admin and member
and here we'll add dot includes
and ro
right. So the role which is provided
here does not includes either admin or
member. In that case we cannot add it.
So here we'll add the statement called
this one. So I'll just copy and paste it
here. And here also we'll add the status
400 then JSON and in the message we'll
add invalid role. So if the role is
neither admin or member then we will
return this response. Now suppose the
role is also correct either role is
admin or member. So in that case
we will fetch the workspace. So I'll
write the comment here fetch workspace
and after that let's add const
workspace equal to await
then prisma dot workspace
dot find unique
and in this one let's add the where
property and provide
ID ID and the id will be workspace ID.
Right? And after this object provide the
comma and provide includes or include
and in this one just add the members
true.
So here we'll get the workspace and
after that we'll add the if statement
and write not of workspace.
Suppose we could not find the workspace.
So let's send the response here. So I'll
write return response do a status for
not four.
Then JSON and the message is workspace
not found.
After that here we'll add the another
comment check creator has admin role.
Now suppose the workspace is available
then we have to check the creator is
admin or not. If the creator is admin
then only they can add the member. So
here let's add the if statement and
provide not of
workspace dot
members dot
and here we'll use the find method.
In this one, let's add the add a
function
and provide the individual member here.
And then it will return the member dot
user ID
equal to user ID.
Then operator and here we will add
member dot ro
equal to
admin.
So when it is true in that case just add
return
and let me just copy this one paste it
here response do a status 4 not one and
then we'll add the JSON and provide the
message
that is
you don't have admin privileges
here we have added not operator right
now suppose the user have the admin
permission. So in this case
let me add another comment. So I'll
write
check if user is already a member.
Suppose we are trying to add a user in
the organization and that user is
already member in that organization. So
first we have to check that. So just add
const
and provide existing member
equal to workspace
dot
members dot find method. And here we'll
add the add function and provide the
individual member in the parameter.
And after that here we'll add the member
dot user id equal to user id like this.
And after that here we'll add the if
statement. If this existing member is
true in this case again we will return
this response. So just copy and paste it
here. that is return dot a status 400
then JSON and in the message we'll add
user is already a member
like this. Now suppose the user is not
the member of this organization then we
have to add it in the members list. For
that here let's add con
member equal to
await and after that let's add the
prisma
dot
workspace member table dot create. Here
we'll create a new data or entry. Now
here we'll add the data property and in
this data property provide the user ID.
In this user id just add the user dot
id. After that we have to provide the
workspace ID.
Then we will provide the role
and after that we will provide the
message.
That's it. So this data will get saved
in the database and after that we can
send the response. So let's add this
response status. I'll just copy this
paste it here. We will write response a
status or let me remove this a status.
We will simply add response dot JSON and
in this one we have to provide the
member. Let me just copy this member.
Paste it here. Then add comma. So we
have provided the member and with that
we'll also add the message and in the
message let's type member added
successfully. So we have created this
controller function that will add a new
member in the workspace
and here we have created another
function to get all workspaces of any
user. Now for these controller function
we have to create the API endpoint. For
that we have to create the routes right.
So here we have to create a folder. So
in this server folder we'll create
another folder called routes.
In this routes folder we'll create a
file. So we'll create a new file and
write the file name workspace routes.js.
Now in this one first we have to import
the express. So let's add import
express from the express package. Using
this express package we will create the
router. So I'll write const workspace
router equal to
express dot router.
Now we have created a router. In this
router we will define different
endpoint. So let's write workspace
router dot get method and in this one
first we have to provide the path it
will be slash and after that we'll add
the controller function. So the
controller function name is get
user workspaces and it has been imported
from this controllers folder. Write the
file name extension js.
Right after that let me just duplicate
this line. And in this one we will
change the type. It will be post.
This is the get method and this one is
the post method. Here we'll add the
path. So the path will be add member
/ add member. And here we'll add the
controller function that is add member.
Add member controller function has been
imported here.
After that we have to export this router
from this file. So let's add export
default and workspace router. That's it.
Now we have to add this workspace router
in our main file that is server.js file.
So let's open server.js. Scroll down
and uh in this one you can see here we
have this inest route. So after that
let's add other routes. So here we'll
add
comment
routes and we'll add app dot use and uh
let's add the path here that is / API/
workspaces
and after that let's provide this
workspace router and now you can see
this workspace router has been imported
here
right now. In this one, we have to add a
middleware also. We will create a custom
middleware that will protect this route.
For that, let's come here in this
sidebar. And uh after that, here
in this server folder, we'll create a
new folder and type the folder name
middlewares.
In this middleware folder, we'll create
a new file and write the file name o
middleware.js.
And here we'll create the middleware
function with the name protect. So just
add export const protect equal to
asynchronous add function. And in this
function parameter we'll get request
response and next function. After that
here we'll add the try catch statement.
Now in this try block first we'll get
the user ID. So let's add const curly
braces user id equal to await. And here
we will use the request
and from this request
we will get the user ID using this o
function.
Right now we'll add the if statement
that will check the user ID is available
or not. So just add not of user ID. It
means when the user ID is not available
in that case we will stop this function.
So just add return and we'll send the
response using response a status for not
one. And then we'll add the JSON
and in this JSON we'll add the message
that is unauthorized.
And suppose the user ID is available. In
that case we will add return
and it will call the next function.
That's it. Now come to this catch block.
So here we'll add the same console log
error and after that we'll add return
dot a status 4.1 and then JSON and here
we'll add the message. It will be error
docode or error dot message. That's it.
So we have created a protect middleware.
So what will happen when we will hit any
route then this protect middleware will
be executed first and it will check when
we have the user ID available then only
it will execute our controller function.
If I come here in this server.js you can
see we have this path and after that we
have this router right. So before
executing the controller function on
this router we have to add that protect
middleware that will protect this route.
So here let's add
protect. Let's import it from the
middleares folder. Add the comma here.
And after that you can see this protect
has been imported from this o
middleware.js.
Now what is happening here when we hit
this route first it will execute this
protect middleware and it will check for
the user ID. If the user ID is available
then only it will come to the controller
function. Like we have this controller
function here. In this controller
function you can see we need this user
ID. Right? So if the user ID is not
available it will not come to this
controller function. It will return the
response that is unauthorized using this
protect middleware. So we have created
the controller function and we have
created the API to get the workspaces
data and add the member in workspace.
After creating the API for workspaces.
Now let's enable the workspace
functionality in our front end. For that
let me close all these files. So I'll
right click and select close saved. It
will close all the files. And here we
have the server folder. Let's collapse
it. And now we will expand the client
folder where we have the front end. Now
in this client folder if I open the src
and then we will open the features and
in this features we have workspace
slice.js file. Let's open it.
Now in this file you can see
here we have the initial state for
workspaces. So in this one we have added
the dummy data right you can see dummy
workspaces that is available in our
asset right. So let me just remove it
here we will initialize it using empty
array.
Then we have the current workspaces or
current workspace. So in this current
workspace we have added the workspaces
index one. So I will remove it and here
we will add null. So the current
workspace will be null and the loading
will be false. Right?
Now in this file we'll add the reducer
function. Using that we can add the data
in the workspaces state. Right? So here
you can see we have the workspaces or
workspace slice where we have the name
initial state and reducers. So here we
have multiple reducers like set
workspaces, set current workspace, add
workspace, update workspace,
then delete workspace and add project,
then add task.
After that here we have the update task
and then we have the delete task. So we
have these
functions in the reducer. Now we'll add
one extra reducer. So
let's come here and uh we'll add the
comma here and provide the
extra reducers
and in this one we'll add the add a
function
like this.
Now in this parameter we will get
builder
and after that within this function
let's add the builder dot add case.
Now in this one let's add
fetch work spaces.
But before that we have to create this
function fetch workspaces. So let me
scroll up. We will create a function
here using that we can fetch the
workspaces from the back end. Right? So
here before initializing this state
let's add
export
con
fetch workspaces
equal to
create a sync thunk. This create a sync
thunk has been imported from
reduxjs/toolkit.
Now in this one
let's add the text called
workspace/fetch
workspaces.
After that we'll add the comma here and
provide the asynchronous add function.
Now in this function parameter we will
add the get token. So let's add curly
braces
get token and within this function we
will add the try catch a statement. Now
in this try block we will make the API
call to
get the
workspaces data right and to make the
API call here we are going to use the
Axio's
package right so first we have to
install it we will open the terminal
and uh you can see this is the backend
terminal right let me change it I'll
come to front end terminal
Now in this one the project is running.
So just add Ctrl C to stop it. And after
that we'll add npm
install
and we will write the package name. So
the package name is Axios
npm install Axios and let's press enter.
So this exhaust package has been
installed and after that we have to add
the back end URL also. So let me start
the project again using npm rundev
and uh after that
we will come here in this client folder
we'll create a file. So create a new
file and write the file name
where we will store the environment
variables.
So this env file is already available
here. So we cannot create it. Let's open
this env file. It is already available.
We have added the color publishable key
in this file. Now in this one we have to
add the base URL or backend URL. So
let's add wheat_base
URL equal to and you can see the backend
server is running at this URL localhost
col 5,000. So just copy and paste it
here. Now in this one we have this
forward slash at the end. So make sure
to remove this. It should end with this
number. Save the changes. So now we have
the base URL. And after that
we will create a file here where we will
add the
axios and in that axio we will add the
base URL. So in this src folder let's
create a new folder and write the folder
name config
and in this configs folder let's create
file and write the file name api dot js.
Now in this file we have to import the
axios. So let's add import Axios from
Axio package and after that we'll add
const API equal to Axio
dot create
and in this one let's provide the base
URL and in this base URL let's add
import
dot meta dot
env that is environment variable file.
Then we'll add dot and then we'll add
the environment variable name wheat base
URL. Let's add it here. So now we have
added the base URL in the AIOS and
created the AIOS with the name API.
Let's export this API from this file.
And after that we can use it in any
other file. So now I'll open the
workspace/js
file and here in this try block we'll
add const
curly braces data equal to await and
here we will use this API import this
API from the config folder that we have
just created and after importing this
API from this config folder here we can
use dot get method
and provide the path path. So let's add
the path here that is / API/workspaces
and here we have to provide the headers
to authenticate our request. So let's
add the headers property and in this
headers property just add the object. In
this object we'll add the authorization
and in this authorization we have to add
the token. So first we'll add the
authorization property here and then
we'll add the back tick. In this back
text we'll add beer and then we have to
insert the token. For that we'll add
dollar sign curly braces and here we'll
add await
and use this get token function
like this. So it will add the token here
and it will authenticate the request.
After that we will get the data. So
let's add the return statement that is
return
data dot workspaces
or we'll add the empty array.
If we don't have the data then we'll add
the empty array. It means there will be
no workspace. Right? Now come to this
catch block and here we'll add console
log
and in this console log let's add the
error. So we have added this error
response data message or error dot
message. Now here also we'll add the
return and it will return the empty
array like this.
So here we have added fetch workspaces
that will fetch the workspace data. If
it is available it will return the list
of workspaces or it will return the
empty array. Now let's come here in the
extra reducers
and here we have the first case right
that is add case and in this add case
let's add this function
fetch work spaces and then we'll add dot
pending
right so then we'll add the comma and
provide the arrow function
and here we'll the estate
and in this add a function we'll add the
estate
dot loading and we'll set the loading
true
right so if I come here you can see we
have this
initial state and in this state we have
the loading false so we will make it
true when the state is pending right
after that again come here we will add
the next case. Right? So, let me just
duplicate this.
We'll add semicolon here and duplicate
this.
So, now we have the another case. So,
just add builder dot add case fetch
workspaces dot fulfilled.
Right? Then here we'll add the function
where we'll get the estate and action.
So, just add a state and action in the
parameter. After that here let's add
a state dot workspaces equal to action
dot payload.
So it will set the workspaces. Right now
we'll add the if statement here. We'll
add if and we'll add action.p payload
do.length
if it is greater than zero. Right? So in
this case just add const
and we'll add the local storage here
right. So let's add con local storage
current workspace id
equal to local storage
dot get item
and in this one let's add current
workspace ID. After that here we'll add
another if statement. So let's add if
and here we will check for this local
storage current workspace ID if it is
available. So in this case we have to
find the workspace. So let's add the if
statement here that is const
find workspace
equal to action dot payload
dot find. And in this one let's add the
add function. Here we'll get the
individual workspace and it will return
workspace do ID
equal to local storage current workspace
ID.
Right now here we'll add another if
statement. So just add if
this find workspace is true. So in this
case let's add the estate dot current
workspace and in this current workspace
we will set the
find workspace.
So this
statement will set the current workspace
in this state. Right? After that we'll
add the else statement also. Let's add
the else statement here. In this one,
we'll add
a state dot current workspace
equal to action
dot
payload. And from this one, we will find
the first workspace. So just add the
index zero. That's it. Now let's add the
else statement for this if. So here
we'll add else statement. And in this
one we'll add the state dot current
workspace
equal to action dot payload and provide
the index zero. Suppose this local
storage current workspace id is not
available. In that case also we'll set
the current workspace equal to action
dot payload index0. Right? And after
that we have to set the loading state.
Right? So here let's add the estate dot
loading property and equal to false. So
the loading will become false.
Right? After that we'll add one more
case. So I'll just copy this one and
paste it here.
In this one we'll add builder dot add
case which workspaces dot and then we'll
add the rejected
right and here we have added the add
function with a state and here we'll add
a state dot loading and make it false.
So just add the false here save the
changes. So we have added this extra
reducer using that we will get the
workspaces data from the database using
the backend API. Next we have to load
the workspaces data when we load the
layout file. So let's open the sidebar
and open the
pages and open layout.jsx file. Now in
this file you can see we have this is
sidebar open. Then we have the loading
and we are getting this loading from
use selector estate workspace right. So
with this loading we will also get the
workspaces. So let's add comma here and
provide
workspaces. So we'll get the workspaces
data from this state. Right? And after
that here we are getting the dispatch
from use dispatch. And after that we
have user from use user right and after
that here we'll get the token. So let's
add con
curly braces
get token
equal to
use o. So use o will get imported from
the
color. You can see use has been imported
from the color/
color react
right and after that here you can see we
have this use effect that will load the
theme. So let it be after that here we
have the use effect that is checking if
the user is not logged in then it will
display the sign-in component right but
before that we will also add one more
use effect. So here let's add
comment
called initial load of workspaces. So
here we'll add use effect.
Then in this use effect I'll add the add
function
and then we'll add the dependency array.
So in this array just add the user
and after that we'll add is loaded.
Now come to this function and in this
function we'll add if statement if
is loaded
and user. So if is loaded is true and
user is available
and
this workspace
dot length
I mean workspaces do.tlength length is
equal to zero.
Right? So in this case we will call the
fetch workspaces. So just add dispatch
and here we'll add
fetch workspaces and import it from the
features folder. And in this one let's
add the curly braces and provide the get
token that is here. So if the workspaces
length is zero then it will call this
fetch workspaces to get the workspaces
data it will initialize the workspaces
right now after that we have the
workspaces data whenever we load our web
page next we have to add one more
functionality right now if I open the
web page
it is not loaded yet
here you can see we have this user
Right? User is logged in. Right? But
after login, we don't have any
organization or workspace. So whenever
we will create a new account or we log
into our account without any
organization, then it will display a
popup or component to create an
organization. for that. Let me just come
back and uh
here
we have this
loading right it will display the
loading animation. So after that let's
add another if statement and it will
check for the user if the user is logged
in then we'll add the and operator and
provide the workspaces.length
is zero. So let's add workspaces.length
is zero. It means the user is logged in
and they don't have any workspaces. So
in this case we'll add return
and in this return let's add a div. Now
in this div let me add some telvin
classes. So I'll add the class name
property provide the minimum height a
screen then flex justify center and item
center so that the component will be
aligned in the center. whatever we will
place in this div. So in this div we
have to add the component that will
display a organization signup form or
create organization form. So let's add
the component here
create organization and import it from
the color. We are getting the suggestion
here. Just click here create
organization.
That's it. If I scroll up, you can see
the create organization has been
imported from the color/color react.
That's it. Now we will save the changes
and open our web page. So you can see it
is displaying this create organization
component where we can upload the image.
For the organization, we have to add the
organization name and slug. slug will be
added automatically according to the
name. Right? So whenever we will log it
will display this popup to create an
organization when we don't have any
organization. So let me create an
organization here. I'll upload one logo.
Then we will add the name. So I'll write
the organization name
create a stack
dev
and after that I'll click on this button
create organization.
So as you can see once we have created
the organization we are redirected to
this homepage or dashboard page and you
can see the organization logo and
organization name and we have total one
workspace right.
So this is the workspace or organization
name great stack dev and if you don't
have any organization it will display
the create organization window or popup
right now after that let me verify the
organization data is saved in the
database or not and this organization
data will get saved in the database
using the ingest function. So let's open
the ingest dashboard first. So in this
ingest dashboard you can see we have the
event called sync workspace from clerk.
If I open it you can see it is executed
successfully. Right? So whenever we'll
create the organization the organization
data will be available in the color
behavgest
function right and you can see this
ingest function is executed
successfully. This ingest function will
add the data in database. So now let me
open the neon database and in this one
come to this workspace table and you can
see here we have the workspace data
right that is the ID name slug we don't
have any description and here we have
the settings this is the empty object so
we have successfully created the new
workspace or organization here we have
the image URL also that we have uploaded
it is working fine Now again come back
to the dashboard that is the project
manager dashboard that we are creating.
So in this one we have this workspace or
organization data in the top left corner
and if I click on this dropdown here we
have the dummy data right. So I'm going
to replace this dummy data here will
display the list of workspace available
for this particular user. And when user
will click on this create workspace, it
will again display that popup to create
a new workspace. For that, let me just
come back to the VS code. And here we
will open sidebar. And in this sidebar,
we have the components. In this
components, you will find workspace
drop-down. JSX file.
Right now, in this one, we need the list
of organizations. For that we are going
to use use organization list. Right? So
just add const
curly braces
equal to use organization list.
So use organization list has been
imported from the color/color react. Now
in this one let's add the object and
provide
user membership
and let's make it true. So here we have
added user memberships pro and after
that here we will get set active
after that we will get user memberships
after that we will get is loaded
like this. Now in this one also we have
to add the functionality to display the
create organization popup right. So
let's add con
curly braces
equal to
use color.
Use color has been imported and from
this use color we can get open
create organization.
That's it. Now here we have these data
and this
component. Right after that here we have
this dispatch navigate and then we have
this on select workspace. Right. So in
this on select workspace we have to set
the active workspace. So let's add set
active and provide the object and in
this object we'll add the organization
property. In this organization property
we'll add the organization ID.
That's it. After that scroll down here
you can see we have this
comment close drop-down on outside
click. So let it be and after that we'll
add another use effect. So let's add use
effect. In this one we'll add the add
function and then we'll add the
dependency array. In this dependency
array we'll add the current workspace
and we'll also add is loaded.
Right now come to this function and here
we'll add the if statement if
the current workspace is available and
is loaded is true. So in this case
we will use
set active and in this set active again
add the object and provide the
organization property and in this
organization property let's add the
current workspace
dot id
that's it so it will set the current
workspace and after that we have to
display the list of workspaces in the
drop-down for that let's scroll down and
here you will find this is open estate
when it is true we are displaying the
list of workspaces right so here we have
the dummy workspace data right so let me
remove it instead of this dummy
workspaces I'll provide
user memberships
dot
data
right so it will display the list of
workspaces where this user is a member.
Correct? And after that we'll add the on
click property
on this div. Right? So here we have the
text called create workspace. When we
click on this button, it will open the
component to create a new workspace. So
let's add on click property. Here in
this on click, we'll add the arrow
function. And here let's add open create
organization function. Right? Then we
will add the semicolon. And here we will
add set is open. And let's make it
false.
So it will close that drop-down.
Correct. After updating it, save the
changes and let's open the web page. So
now you can see if I click on this
dropdown here, we have only one
workspace.
And this workspace image is not visible.
So I'll correct it. And here we have the
button create workspace. If I click
here, it is opening this
component to create another workspace.
Right?
So to fix this issue of workspace name
and image, I'll just come back here.
And in this map you can see we have
added WS that is workspace. So instead
of this one we'll add one object so that
we can dstructure the properties and in
this one we'll add the organization.
So in this data we'll get the
organization property and in that
organization property we will get the
name, image and number of user. Right?
So let's update it here. We will add
organization do ID. Then we'll add
organization do id here also. Then we'll
add organization dot image url. Here
we'll add organization dotname.
And after that let's add organization
dot name. And here we'll add
organization dot members count.
And here we'll add organization do ID.
That's it. Save the changes and come
back here.
Now let me refresh it. I'll just click
here. Still the image is not visible. So
I'll just come back and here let me
update it. It will be image URL
like this.
Now it is correct. Save the changes and
come back here. Now you can see we have
the list of organizations with the logo,
name and number of members. And when we
click on anyone from the list that will
become the active organization right or
active workspace and when we click here
it will open the component to create a
new workspace. So let me create another
workspace here. I'll write greater stack
marketing. I'll write MKT.
And here we'll add any other image. So
let me use this one white image and
click on create organization.
So now another organization has been
created and it is asking to invite new
members. So we can add a new member also
or we can skip this one. We will invite
the members later.
So we have created another organization.
So now you can see in this dropdown we
have two workspaces that is greatest
stack dev and greatest stack marketing
and we have the name, image and total
number of members. If I click on the
second one, you can see it will become
the active workspace, right? And you can
see the workspace image here, the name
and here we have total two workspaces.
We can switch from here. And if I click
on this one, it will open the
component to create a new organization
or workspace.
So we have added the functionality for
user authentication. And with that we
have also added the functionality to
create an organization and switch
between different organization.
After adding the authentication and
organization feature and connecting it
with the front end. Next we have to
create the APIs for the project so that
we can add a new project. We can add the
task in the project. Right? So for that
let me just come back to the VS code and
let me close all these files.
Close saved. Now open the sidebar and
let's come here in this server folder
because we have created the back end in
this server. Now in this server folder
we have the controllers folder. So in
this controllers folder we'll create a
new file and write the file name project
controller.js.
In this one, let me add the comment. So
here we'll add
create project. So here we will add the
controller function. Using that we can
create a new project. So just add export
con create project equal to
async arrow function. In this function
parameter we will get request and
response
like this. So we have created the
function called create project. In this
function we'll add the try catch
statement right and in this catch block
let's add
console log
and here we'll provide this error and
after that here we'll add the response.
So just add response dot a status
500.
Then we'll add the message using JSON
method. So in this JSON let's add
message property. It will be error
docode or error dot message. So we have
added the function with try catch block.
And in the catch block we have added
this code and the try block is empty.
Now let me just duplicate this function.
But before that we'll add the comment
also. So let me add the comment here.
update project and copy this function.
Paste it here. So we have another
function called update project and here
we'll add the function name update
project. Right now let's add the comment
called add member to project. So let's
add the comment and after that again
copy this function here
and in this one let's add the function
name add member. So you can see we have
created three functions that is create
project, update project and add member.
Now let me complete the functions one by
one. So I start with the first one that
is create project. Now in this one first
we need the user ID. So let's add const
curly braces user ID and we will get
this user ID from the request. Right? So
just add equal to await
request dot.
So this o function is added using the
color. After that we need the data from
the request body. So whenever we are
creating a project we need the project
data like workspace ID, project
description, project name, a status, a
start date, end date, team members, team
lead, progress and priority. So let's
add const
curly braces and here let's get these
data
like
workspace ID description name a status a
start date end date team members team
lead progress and priority equal to our
request dot body. So we have to send
these data on this API.
After that we'll add the
comment. So let's add the comment. Check
if user has admin role for workspace.
So if the user is admin in this
workspace then only they can create the
project. So I'll write
const
workspace equal to await and here we
will use Prisma. So we are not getting
the suggestion for the Prisma, right? So
I'll open this sidebar and here you can
see we have the configs folder where we
have the Prisma.js file. Let's open it.
And after that here if I type
Prisma, we are getting the suggestion.
So just import the Prisma from config
folder. And here we'll add the file name
extension js like this. Now from this
Prisma we will find the
workspace table. Then we'll add dot find
unique.
In this one we have to add the object
and provide the where property and
provide the object ID and the id is
workspace ID.
Then we will add comma and here we will
add include property. In this include
property let's add the
members. And in this one let's add
include
and provide the object where we will
provide user
true.
So it will add the user data in this
workspace. Right now let's add the if
statement if not of workspace.
Suppose we could not find this
workspace. In that case, we'll return
the response. So let's add return
response dot status 4.4. Then we'll add
the message using JSON method. So just
add JSON. Message is workspace not
found. After that we'll add the if
statement. And here we'll add not of
workspace
dot
members dot sum.
And uh here let's provide the add a
function
where we'll add the member.
Let me just close this if
and uh create the arrow function here.
Then we'll add member dot user id is
equal to user id
and operator and provide member. equal
to admin.
So in this if statement we are checking
if this user is not admin because we
have added not operator here. So here
we'll add return. So let me just copy
this one. Copy and paste it here. return
response a status 4 not three and after
that we'll add the JSON and here we'll
add the message so let me add the
message called you don't have permission
to create project in this workspace
after that let's add the comment so I'll
write get team lead using email
right so here we'll add con team lead
equal equal to await and here we'll add
Prisma dot user dot find unique
and in this one let's add the where
property and provide the email here in
this email just provide
team lead that we are getting from the
body after that we'll add select and
here we'll add curly braces id equal to
true id colon true
right so now we have the team lead next
we can create the project so let's add
con project equal to await
and here let's add
prisma dot project dot create method
now let's add the object here and
provide the data now in this data we
will store the workspace ID.
After that we will store the name. Then
description.
Then we will add the status.
After that we will store the priority.
Then we will store progress.
After that we will store team lead. In
this team lead, let's add
team lead dot id. Here we'll add the
question mark. If it is available, it
will be added here. After that, let's
add the start date. So, just add a start
date and it will be
a start date question mark if it is
available. Let's add new date
and provide the start date
and then we'll add colon null.
So if it is available it will convert it
into date. Else it will add null. After
that we'll add the end date also. So
let's add end date.
And here also we'll add the same thing.
So just copy this.
Paste it here.
Here we will add end date and end date.
That's it. So we have created a project.
It will be added in the database. After
that we have to add members to project
if they are in the workspace. So here
let's add the comment.
We will write add members to project if
they are in the workspace. So we'll add
the if statement and here we'll add the
team members
question mark dot length.
So if the length is greater than zero.
So in this case we have to find the
members list to be added right. So just
add con
members to add
and it will be one empty array.
After that here we'll add the workspace
dot members dot for each
and here we'll add the arrow function.
So let's add the individual member
and create the add function. Then add
the function here and write if statement
if the team members
dot
includes
and here we'll add the
member dot user dot email. So if this
individual member email id is included
in this team members then it should be
added in the project right. So here
we'll add the if statement. So just add
the members to add and then add dot push
and here we'll add the member dot user
dot id. So we have to find the user ID.
it will be added in this one that is
members to add right this is an array
that's why we have added push so now we
have the list of team members with their
ID to be added in the project now to add
the project member we have to add a new
entry in the database if I open our
Prisma schema file you can see here we
have user workspace then workspace
member
Right? So in this one we have to add
these data but this is the workspace
member. Then we have the project. Right?
And uh after that we have the project
member. Right? So we have to add the
data in this one that is project member.
We have to provide the
user ID and then we have to provide the
project ID.
Correct? And these are the relations
with other table and this ID is
autogenerated. So we have to provide the
user ID and project ID only in the
project member. So I'll just come here
and uh
here let's add
await and provide
Prisma dot
project member. Let me add it inside
this
if block.
Right. So let me move it here
like this. So we have added a weight
prisma.p project member
dot
create many
and uh after that let's add the object
here where we'll add the data property
and in this data property let's add the
members to add then we'll add dot map
method and here we'll add the individual
member id and create the arrow function
now Here let's add parenthesis then
object and it will be
project id
and uh in this project id let's store
the project
dot id after that we will store the user
ID and in this user ID let's add the
member ID
that's it so it will add the data in the
database that will add the project
member. Right? Now, here we have the
project and here we have the project
member.
Correct? Now, after that, we will add
one more variable where we will store
the project data with the member also
and that will be sent in the response.
So just add const
project with members
equal to await and here we'll add Prisma
dot project dot find unique
and here we'll add the object and
provide where
and let's add the ID. So the id is
project
dot id. After that let's add includes.
So it will include the other data. So
let's add include. And in this one just
add the member property
or members property. And here let's add
include and provide the user property.
And in this user just add true.
After that let's add the
tasks also and in this task let's add
include
and after that let's provide the
assigne and here let's make it true
and after that we'll add the comments
also. So let's add comments
and in this comments again add includes
and uh let's add the user and make it
true
like this. And after that we have to add
the owner property.
In this owner property let's make it
true.
That's it. So here we have the project
with members and with that we have also
added the task and in this task we have
added the comments right and after that
we can send this projects with members
in the response so let's add the
response dot JSON
now here we have to add the project
property so let's add the project
property and it will be this project
with members
after that we'll add the message
property
and in this message property let's add
the string that is project created
successfully.
That's it. So now we have created a
controller function using that we can
create a new project. Right? Next let's
come to the second function that is
update project.
Now in this one we have this try block.
So in this try block again we need the
user id. So I'll write
const
user id it will be await request do
after that again we need the data from
the body. So here also we'll add con
curly braces and we will get the ID
then workspace ID description name
status a start date end date progress
and priority right and here we have the
ID also so that we can update the
particular project and we will get this
data from the request dobody after that
let's add
comment here
check if user has admin role control for
workspace. So again we will add the same
thing. Let me just come here,
copy this one
and paste it here.
that is const workspace equal to update
prisma dotworkspace dotfind where id is
workspace id includes members include
user true
right and after that let's add the if
statement
not of workspace so if we could not find
the workspace we will send the response
so just add return response a status for
not four and the message is workspace
not found. So here you can see we have
added if statement not of workspace.
Suppose if the workspace is not
available we will send this message in
the response. Now suppose the workspace
is available. So here we'll add the
another if statement and write not of
workspace
dot members dot sum.
Then we will add the add function here.
And here we'll add the
individual member and provide member dot
user id
equal to user ID
and operator we will add the member
dot ro
equal to
admin.
So what is happening here? It will check
the
user is the member
and user is admin in this workspace.
Right? But suppose the user is not admin
in this workspace then what will happen?
So here we have added not operator. It
means when the user is not admin in that
case we will find the project and we
will check the user is the team lead in
this project or not. Right? Now suppose
the user is already admin then we will
come to this line and here we will
simply update the project right but if
the user is not admin so here let's find
the project first so just add const
project
equal to await and then write the Prisma
dot project dot find unique
And let's add the where property and
provide the id.
So it will find the project. After that
here let's add the if statement if not
of project. Suppose the project is not
available
with this id. Right? So just add the
return statement and provide this
response dot status 4.4 four and the
message is project not found. Right? Now
we'll add the else statement.
If the project is available then we will
check the role. So let's add else if
and in this else if let me write
project dot team lead
not equal to
user ID
right so if it is not the team lead so
let's add the return
and here we'll add the response so just
add response dot a status
4.3 then we'll add the message you don't
have permission to update projects in
this workspace
right now if the user is admin then they
can directly come here and we'll write
const
project
equal to await and we'll use prisma
dot project dot update. We will use the
update method here to update the
project. So in this object we'll add the
where property and provide the ID.
Then we'll add comma and provide the
data. So in this data let's add the
object and provide the workspace ID.
Then
let's provide the description.
Then we will provide the name. After
that we will provide the status.
Then let's provide the
priority.
After that we will provide the progress.
Then provide a start date and end date.
So I'll just copy from here a start and
end date.
Paste it here.
So again you can see we have the
workspace ID, description, name, a
status, priority, progress, a start date
and end date. Right after that we will
send the response. So let's add response
dot JSON and here let's add the project
that is updated here. So just add the
project and then we'll add comma message
property and here we'll add the message
project updated successfully. That's it.
So here we have created the function
using that we can update the project.
Now we have the third function here that
is add member to project. So let's
complete this function also. So in this
try block let's add con
curly braces. we will get the user id
from
request. So just add user id equal to
await request do.
After that let's add const project id.
We will get the project ID from the
body. So just add
request or instead of body we will get
it from the parameter. So let's add dot
paradams.
So we will get it from the URL paradoms
and after that we'll add email and we
will get the email from the body. So
let's add con curly braces email equal
to
request dobody.
So you can see we are getting the user
ID.
So this is the user ID who will add the
member. Then we have the project ID. We
will get this project ID from the URL
path or the URL parameters. After that
we will get the email id and this email
id will be sent in the request in the
body. Now after that let's add the
comment check if user is project lead.
So let's add con project equal to await
and here we will use prisma
dot project dot find unique
and let's add the where property and
provide the id here. So the ID is
project ID.
After that let's add the comma and
include. In this include let's add the
member
and in this members property let's add
include and provide the user and let's
make it true. So it will add the user
data also in this project.
After that here let's add the if
statement if not of project.
So in this case we will send the
response. So just add response
dot a status 44 and the message is
project not found. After that we'll add
another if statement.
If
the project dot team lead not equal to
user id right so if the user is not the
team lead so in this case we'll add
return response do a status 44 and then
we'll add the message here using JSON
method so it will be only project lead
can add members
now suppose the user is team lead so in
this case let's add the comment check if
the user is already a member. So if we
are trying to add a user in the project
and this user is already a member on
this project. So here let's add con
existing member equal to project
dot members dot find method
and here we'll add the add a function
and in this function parameter we'll get
the individual member
and after that let's add member do email
id equal to email id
right after that let's add the if
statement
if existing member is true right so in
this case we will send the response so
let's add return response do a status
400 json and the message is user is
already a member now after that let's
add
con
user
equal to await.
Then we'll add the Prisma dot user
dot
find unique
and in this one we'll add the where
property and provide the email id.
So using this email id we will get the
particular user and after that let's add
the if statement not of user. Suppose we
could not find the user with this email
id. So let's add the return statement.
And here we'll add a status 4.4 and the
message is user not found. Now suppose
the user is available with this email
id. Then we will add the
data in database. So let's add const
member
equal to await. Then we will add the
Prisma
dot
project member
dot create. And after that let's add the
data. And in this data simply add the
user ID
right. And in this user ID let's add the
user dot id property. After that we'll
add the project ID.
That's it. We need only these two data.
So this user will be added in this
project. It means the member is added in
the project. After that let's send the
response. So let's add response.json.
And in this one let's add the object and
provide this member
who is added. After that we'll add the
comma and provide the message here. So
the message is member added
successfully. That's it. So here we have
created three controller function that
is add member then update project and
create project. Now using these
controller function we'll create the API
endpoint. So let's create the routes. So
I'll open the sidebar. Here we have the
routes folder. In this one create a new
file and write the file name project
routes.js.
Now in this one we'll create the router.
So just add import express from the
express package and then we'll add con
project router equal to express dot
router. So we have created the project
router. Now in this project router let's
add different path. So we'll add the API
type that is post
and then we'll provide the path. it is
slash and then provide comma and here
we'll add the controller function name
that is create
project.
So you can see the create project has
been imported from this controllers
folder project controller.js file write
the file name extension js.
So here we have added create project.
Now let me just duplicate this and here
it will change the type it will be put
like this and the path will be same.
Here we will update the controller
function. So it will be
update project. So update project has
been imported. Now let's duplicate it.
Here we will change the type. It will be
post. And then we have to update the
path. So it will be / colon and provide
the project id.
So this project id will be added using
url padams. After that we'll add /
add member.
So first we'll add the project ID then
add member and after that here we have
to add the controller function that is
add member. So you can see the add
member controller function has been
imported. Next we have to export this
router from this file. So let's add
export default project router. Now let's
open our main file that is server.js
file. And in this one
here let's add app dot use and provide
the API path. It will be / API/ projects
like this. And after that we have to add
the middleware that is product. So the
product middleware has been added. And
after that we'll add the
project router. So the project router
has been imported. If I come here you
can see it has been imported. So here we
have created the APIs to add a new
project, update the project and add a
new member in the project.
Now we have to create the APIs to add
task in this project. For that we'll
create the controller file. So let's
open the sidebar and in this
controller folder we will create a new
file and write the file name task
controller.js.
Now in this one first we'll create the
controller function to create a new
task. So let's add the comment that is
create task and after that we'll create
the function here. So let's add export
const create task equal to
async arrow function. Now in this
function parameter we will get request
and response and after that let's add
the try catch statement.
Now in this try block we will
use the request to get the user ID. So
let's add con
curly braces
user id and let's get this user id from
the request
dot
o function and before this we will add
the await also like this. So now we have
the user ID. After that we need the task
data that needs to be added in the
project.
So I'll write const curly braces.
First we need the project ID.
After that we need the title.
Then we need description.
After that we need type.
After that we will get the status
priority and assigne ID.
After that here we'll get the due date
also. So let's add the due date
equal to
request dobody. So
we have to send these data on this API.
After that let's add const origin equal
to
request
dot get method
and here we will add origin.
After that let's add the comment. So
I'll write
check if user has admin role for
project. So first we need to find the
project using this
project id. So I'll write con project
equal to
await
and then we'll use prisma.
import the prisma from config folder and
add the file name extension.js.
Now let's add prisma dot
project dot
find unique
in this one let's add the where property
and then we have to provide the id so
the id is project id that we are getting
from the request body after that let's
add the include property in this include
let's add the members and uh after that
let's add include
and here we'll and curly braces
user property true. So in the members it
will add the users data right after that
here we'll add another if statement and
write not of project suppose we could
not find any project with this project
id right so in this case we'll send the
response so let's add return response do
a status 44 and the message is project
not found
now suppose the project is available. So
here we'll add else if. So in this else
if let's add the project dot team lead
not equal to
user ID.
So if this user is not a team lead in
this project in this case let's add
return. So I'll just copy this statement
paste it here
and uh here we'll write response a
status 4 not3 and then we'll add the
message. So the message is
you don't have admin privileges for this
project.
Let me update this not equal to.
Right. After that again add
else if and here we'll add the assigne
id
and then we'll add not of project dot
members
dotfind.
And here let's add the add function
provide individual member
and it will return the member dot user
id. So we'll add user dot id
equal to
assigne id
right. So in this case
we have to send the response. So let's
add
return
response do a status for not three and
here we'll add the message. So the
message is assigne is not a member of
the project or workspace.
Right now after that we'll add const and
here we'll create the task. So let's add
task
equal to await. And now we will add the
Prisma
dot
task dot create method.
And here we have to add the data. So
let's add the data property and provide
the project ID first. Then we have to
provide the title.
After that we will provide the
description.
Then provide priority.
After that we will provide the assigne
id
and then let's provide the a status
right then add comma and here we'll add
the due date in this due date let's add
new
date and
here we'll provide the due date.
So here we have created a new task. This
task will be added in the database.
Now in this task we will add the assigne
details also. So here let's add const
task with assigne
equal to await and then provide Prisma
dot
task dot
find unique
and after that here let's add the where
property and provide the id. So the id
is task dot id. Then we will provide the
comma and provide include. In this
include just add the
assigne and it will be true.
So it will add the assigne data also.
Right? After that we can send the
response here. So let's add
response.json.
And here we have to add the task. So
let's add the task property.
And in this task provide this task with
assigne.
After that we have to add the message
also. So let's add the message property.
And the message text is task created
successfully. Now come to the catch
block. And in this catch block simply
add console log error. Then we'll add
response dot a status 500. Then we'll
add dot JSON method and provide the
message property that is error docode or
error dot message. So we have created
this controller function. Using that we
can create a new task. After that we
need to create another controller
function. Using that we can update the
task. Right? So scroll down add the
comment here
update task right now let me just copy
the same task from here
let's copy it
and paste it here.
Here we will change the name. So first
update the function name that is update
task. It is also a synchronous add
function with try catch block inside
this function. Then here we need to get
the task right. So let's add const
task equal to await
and then we'll add the Prisma
dot task dot find unique.
And after that in this one just add
where
and here let's add the id. So the id
will be request dot paradams. So in the
API URL parameter we'll add the task id
right. So just add paradams dot id.
So here we'll get the task id and we
will find the task using this id using
the prisma dot task dotfind unique.
Right after that
here let's add the if statement if and
provide not of task.
So if we could not find the task in this
condition we'll add the return
statement. So let's add return
response status 44 and JSON message is
task not found. After that we will get
the user id from the request o it is
correct. Then let me remove the data
from the body. We will use it later and
remove the origin also.
So here we have the user ID that we are
getting from the request do method.
Right. And after that
here we have to find the project
right. So here we have project equal to
await then prisma dot project dotfind
unique where ID is
this particular task dot
project ID
and after that here we have include and
in this one we have added members
include user true right now here we have
added if not of project suppose the
project is not available
in this variable. Right? So here we'll
send the message that is project not
found. Then we have added else if
statement and here we have added you
don't have admin privileges
for this project.
Right? And remove this last if
statement.
So I'll remove this one.
That's it. And after that
here we'll add const
and let's add updated task
equal to await. And let's use the Prisma
dot task dot update method.
Using this we will update the task in
database. Right? And here we have the
previous task data. Let me remove it.
And uh let's remove this one also. So
here we have updated task. It is equal
to await prisma task update. Now here
let's add where
and provide the id. So it will be
request dot params dot id. So this is
the task id. After that we have to
update the data. So let's add the data
property and we will get it from the
request dot body. That's it. So it will
update the task right and uh after that
we will send the message also and we'll
also send the updated task right. So
just add response.json
task property and in this task property
provide this updated task correct and
then we have to add the message. So the
message is
task updated successfully and then we
have this catch block. So we have
created the controller function to
update any task. Next we have to create
a function using that we can delete any
task. Right? So let's come here add the
comment delete task and let me just copy
this function from here.
Let's copy and paste it here.
Right now in this one we have the try
catch block. We have the same statement
in the catch block. And here we have the
try block.
Let's start with the function name. So
the function name should be delete task.
Right now let's remove this and this one
also. First we will get the user ID from
the request.
After that we need the task ID from the
body. So here we'll write
const curly braces
task ids
equal to
request dot body
right and after that let's find the
task. So just add con task equal to
await and here we'll add Prisma
dot task dot find many
we can delete many task right so here
we'll add
this object and provide where and then
we will add curly braces
id and curly braces
in
task ids. So it will delete all the task
with this ids
right and after that let's add if
statement if
the task dotlength
is equal to zero. So in this case let's
add
return
response a status 44 JSON message and
the message is task not found.
So here we have the
task ids and using these ids we will
find all the tasks. Suppose we don't
find any task here. The task length is
zero. Then we'll display this message in
the response. Right? Now suppose the
task is available. This length is
greater than zero. Right? So in this
case,
let's add
con project equal to await prisma.
project.findique.
Then we'll add where id and in this id
let's add the task index zero dot
project id
it will be tasks like this and after
that we have added include let me remove
the comment from here we have added
include members include user true I'll
remove this comment from here also
so here we have added added this
project. Right? Now here we have added
not of project. If the project is not
available, we will return the response
project not found. And if the user is
not
team lead, right? Then we will return
this response. You don't have admin
privileges for this project.
Correct? After that here we'll add
await
prisma dot
task dot delete menu
right and after that here we'll add
where and provide the id and in this one
we'll add the object provide in
task ids so it will delete all the tasks
Right after that we'll send the response
using this response dojson and then
we'll add the message property. So the
message will be task deleted
successfully
like this. So here we have created
another function to delete the task. Now
using these controller function we'll
create the APIs. Right? For that
let's create a new file. And uh here in
this
routes folder we'll create a new file
and write the file name task routes.js.
Here we'll create the router. So let's
add import express from the express
package. And after that let's add const
task router equal to express dot router.
So we have created a router. In this
router, we'll add the end point. So I'll
write this task router dot post method
and provide the path slash and then
we'll add the controller function create
task. Create task has been imported.
Here we'll add the file name extension
js in this line.
Correct? Now let me just duplicate this
line. Here we'll add the type put
like this. And now we'll add the id
here. Just add colon ID. That will be
the task ID. And here we have to provide
the controller function
update task. It has been imported. Now
duplicate this line. And here we will
add the type post.
Right? And here we'll add the path
delete
/ delete and provide the controller
function called delete task. So the
delete task function has been imported.
After that we have to export this router
from here. So just add export default
task router. Now let's open our main
file server.js.
And in this one just duplicate this
line.
Correct? And here we'll change the path.
So it will be / API/ task. Then we'll
add the product middleware. And after
that we'll add the
task router. So you can see the task
router has been imported. So we have
created the API to create a new task,
update the task and delete the task.
Now we have to create the controller
function for comments. It means when we
have created the task, user can add the
comments on the task. For that we have
to create the API. So let's create the
controller functions. So first we'll
create a file here. In this controllers
folder, create a new file and write the
file name comcontroller.js.
Now in this one first we'll add the
controller function to add comment. So
let's add the comment here. Add comment.
And then we'll add the function here
export con add comment equal to async
add arrow function. Then we'll add
request and response in this parameter.
After that let's add the try catch
statement. And after that in this catch
block we'll add the statement from
previous function. So I'll just copy
this and paste it here
like this. So here we have added console
log and response status 500 JSON and the
message is error docode or error dot
message.
Now let's come here in the try block and
in this try block first we need the user
ID. So I'll write con user ID equal to a
request do
after that we'll add const curly braces.
Let's add the comment
and then we'll get the task ID and we'll
get these data from the request body. So
let's add request dot body.
Right after that we'll add check if user
is project member. So if the user is a
project member then only they can add
the comment. So I'll write const
task equal to await
prisma and here we'll add the file name
extension dot js in this import
statement. Then we'll add prisma dot
task dot
find unique and then we'll add the where
property and provide
id. So the id will be task id right. So
now we have the task here and after that
let's add const
project.
Let's find the project. So I'll write
project equal to await
prisma
dot project dot find unique.
And uh after that let's add the where.
And here let's add the ID. So the ID is
task dot project ID
like this. And after that let's add
include.
And here we'll add
members.
And again add include.
And here we'll add the user.
And let's make it true. So it will add
the user data in this project data. Now
suppose the project is not available. So
I'll write if not of project.
So in this case let's add the return and
provide response dot a status
4.4 and then JSON and message is project
not found. Now the project is available.
Then what will happen? Then we'll add
con member
equal to project dot
members dot find
and here we'll add the individual member
and create the add function. So I'll
write member and uh let's create the add
a function here. And after that let's
add the member dot user id
equal to
user id that we are getting here right
and uh after that
let's add the if statement. If not of
member it means this user is not the
project member. So in this case let's
add the return
and we'll add the a status 43 and the
message is you are not member of this
project. Right? Now suppose this member
is true. It means the user is the
project member. Right? So in this case
we can create the comment. So let's add
con
comment equal to
await and here we'll add
Prisma dot comment dot create
and after that let's add the data and in
this data simply add curly braces
provide the task ID and comment
And then we'll add the user ID also.
Let me move it in the new line
like this. So you can see we have added
data. In this data we have added task
ID, comment and user ID. Then we'll add
the comma here and provide
include. And here let's add
user
and make it true.
That's it. Now after that we can send
the response. Right? So here we'll add
response.json
and let's add the comment here. So this
comment will be added in the response.
So we have created the controller
function. During that we can create a
new comment on the task.
If I come here you can see this content
is not used. So this is the comment
content right? So let's scroll down and
you can see in this database we are
adding task ID and then we have to add
this one content. Let's correct it. It
is task ID, content and user ID. That's
it. Save the changes. Now it is used.
Right? Next we have to add another
controller function. Using that we can
get comments
for individual task. Right? So here
we'll add one controller function. So
I'll write con
or we will export this function. So I'll
write export con get task comments equal
to async arrow function and in this
function parameter we'll get request and
response.
After that let's add the try catch
statement and in this catch block we'll
add this statement from here. After that
in this try block first we need the task
ID. So let's add con
curly braces task id equal to request
dot paradams. So from the
API padoms we will get the task id right
and after that let's add con
comments equal to await and provide the
prisma
dot
comment dot
find many
and in this one let's add the object
provide Here
let's add the
task ID right then we'll add comma
include and here let's include the user
data. So let's add user true.
So here we have added this
statement using that we'll get the
comments right after that we can send
this comments in the response. So let's
add
response dojson
and in this JSON we'll add the object
and provide this comments.
That's it. So we have added the
controller function to get the comments
on a individual task. Now using these
controller function we have to create
the API endpoint. For that we have to
create the routes correct. So let's
create a new file in this routes folder
and write the file name comment
routes.js
and here we have to create the router.
So I'll write import express from the
express package. Then we'll add const
comment router
equal to
express dot router.
Now in this comment router we have to
add the method post and provide the
path. It will be slash and then we'll
add the add
comment controller function. So this add
comment controller function has been
imported. just add js file name
extension and uh after that let's
duplicate this line
here we'll add the path colon task id
right and here we'll add the type get so
this is the type get and here we'll add
the controller function get task
comments so this get task comments has
been imported after that we have to
export this comment route router. So
let's add export default comment router
and then we will add it in the main file
that is server.js. So duplicate this
line and here we'll add the path. So the
path will be / API/ comments then
protect middleware and here we'll add
comment router. So this comment router
has been imported from the comment
routes js file. So we have added the API
using that we can add the comment and we
can get the list of comments on any
task. Next we have to add one more
functionality here. Previously we have
created this task controller
and in this task controller you can see
we have this function create task. So
whenever a new task gets created we have
to send an email also to all users. For
that we are going to integrate the
sending email using ingest function. So
the ingest function will send the emails
to all user whenever a new task is
created.
To send an email we need a package
called node mailer. So let's open web
browser and in the new tab we will
search for node mailer.
Open this website.
And here you can see the command npm
install node mailer. We have to use this
to install this package. After that you
can see the step how to use it.
So to create the transporter we have to
add node miller.create transport. And in
this one we have to provide these data
where we'll add the SMTP details like
SMTP host and then username and
password. After that we will create the
sender using this transporter dot send
email or send mail. So we have this send
mail function where we will add the
email the sender email then receiver
email right and then we have to add the
subject
right and then we have to add the
message either in the HTML
or text. In this text, we can simply add
the text
or we can use the HTML to add the
formatted text like a HTML format. So to
use it, I'll just come back to the VS
code. Open the terminal
and uh let's come to the backend
terminal.
Here it is. This is the backend server.
So project is running. I'll write
control C to stop it. And here we'll add
this command npm install node mailer.
Press enter.
So it has been installed. After that I
start the project again using npm run
server.
So now the backend server is again
running. Now we will hide this terminal
and let's open the sidebar. In this
config folder we'll create a new file
and write the file name node mailer.js.
js.
So we have added node miller.js file in
this config folder and in this one first
we have to import the node miller
package. So just add import node miller
from node miller. After that we have to
create the transporter like this.
So I'll just come back and copy this.
and paste it here.
I'll remove this comment and remove this
secure property also.
So here we have the host port o then we
have the user and pass that is password.
So after creating this transporter here
we have to create a function that will
send the email. For that again come back
to the document on this node mailer and
we will copy this function.
Let's copy this one
and come here.
Let's paste it here. And after that
here I'll create a function. I'll write
const
send email
equal to
asynchronous add a function.
Now within this function let's move this
code.
So it will send an email and it will
return some data. Right? So here I'll
write const
response
equal to await transporter dot send
mail. Right now here we have to add the
sender email id. After that we have to
provide the receiver email id. Then
subject and then we will provide the
html. So instead of this text we will
simply provide the HTML
remove this comment. Now let me remove
this dummy data from here.
And here we will get these data
from our parameters. Right? So here in
this parameter let's add curly braces.
We will get the two that is the receiver
email id. Then we'll add
subject
and after that we'll get the body data.
Right? So let's provide the two here.
After that we will provide the subject
and provide the comma and then provide
the body.
We will provide this body in HTML.
Right? And here we have to add the
sendered email id. So to get the sender
email id and these SMTP data we have to
use any SMTP provider. For that let's
come back to the web browser and here we
will open
Bravo. You can use any SMTP provider.
So I'm going to use this
and uh
here you need to create an account. So,
I'll click on sign up for free
and let me continue with my Google
account.
After that, in the right side, you will
find your profile name. Let's click
here. And uh then I'll go to settings.
And in the left side, you will find this
SMTP and API. Let's click here.
So here you will find the SMTP server or
host name, then port number and then
your SMTP email.
Right? So we need to store these data in
the environment variable. Right? So I'll
just come back to the VS code
and let's open the server folder. Then
open env file in this backend server.
Here we have these
environment variables. Right? And after
that here we'll add a space. And let's
add
sender email. So the sender email will
be the email id that we have used to
create the brao account. Right? So I'll
write the email id here that is
user.grad greatest stack@gmail.com.
I have used this email
and after that we will store the
username. So I'll write SMTP
user and this is the SMTP user. I'll
just copy and paste it here.
After that we'll add the SMTP pass that
is password. So here we have this
password
right. So we have multiple passwords
here. I'll create one more here. So
I'll click on this button generate new
SMTP key. Here we'll add the name. So
this is the project management
and click on generate.
So here we have the key. I'll just copy
this and paste it here.
So we have added the sender email id,
smtp user and password. Now just come
back here in the node mailer and here we
will get the sender email from the
environment file that is environment
variable file. So I'll write
process dot env dot
and the environment variable name sender
email
right and after that let's add the
username and password in this
transporter. So first we'll add this
SMTP host.
Let's just copy it.
Copy and paste it here.
then provide the email and password
right so it is also added in the
environment variable so I'll remove this
and provide process dot env
dot
SMTP
user
and uh let's just copy this paste it
here and here we'll add SMTP pass.
So we have configured this node mailer
to send an email. After that let's
export this send email function from
this file. So I'll write
export default send email and using this
function we can send the email right and
here we have the response. So this
function will return the response. So
here let's add
return
response.
So whenever we will call the send email
and provide the
receiver email id, subject and body, it
will send the email and return the
response. And we can call this function
from any file because we have exported
it from this file. After that,
we have to create the ingest function
that will send the email whenever the
task gets created.
So, I'll just come to sidebar.
We will come to inest folder and open
index.js file.
In this one, you can see we have created
these functions, right? And we have
already sync these functions with the
ingest application. Now we'll create one
more function.
So first we'll add the comment here.
Let's add the comment inest function to
send email on task creation.
And I'll write const
send task assignment email and it will
be inest dot create function.
Now in this one let's add the object and
provide the id. So in this id I'll write
send task assignment email then comma
and another object here we'll add the
event. So let's add the event it will be
app/ task dot assigned
right and after that let's add the
function here. So I'll write a sync add
arrow function and in this function
parameter
we will get the event and a step. So
I'll write event and a step here and
within this function let's get the task
data from this event. So I'll write
const
curly braces
task ID and then let's get the origin
also.
equal to
event dot data. So from this event we
will get the task id and origin. And
after getting it
here let's find this task. So I'll write
const
task equal to await. Then use Prisma dot
task dot find unique
and after that let's add where
id and provide this task id. So it will
find the particular task and in this one
we have to include some data. So just
add include
here we will add assigne
and make it true.
So it will add the assigne data and
after that it will also add the project
data. So just add project
true.
After getting the task data now we have
to send the email. So here we'll add
await
send email and let's import this
function. Click here.
I'll scroll up. You can see send email
has been imported from the node
mailer.js file.
And after that
in this one we have to provide one
object. So first we'll add the two
property.
In this two we will add the task dot
assigne
dot email.
So this is the receiver email. After
that we have to add the subject here. In
this subject let's add the message.
So I'll write double quote new task
assigned
or let me write new task assignment in
and then we'll add the project data.
Right? So to insert the project data
here we'll add the template literal. So
let me convert it in back text remove
the double quote and use back text here
so that we can add dollar sign curly
braces to use the template lit. Now
we'll add the task dot project
dot name. You can see in this task we
have included the project data and in
this project we will get the name also.
So the subject will be new task
assignment in project name.
Right? Now add comma and then we have to
add the third property that is body.
In this body also we'll add tactics and
uh after that here you can add more
details about this task. So you can add
the assign name like I'll write hi and
provide the dollar sign curly braces
and provide the task
dot assenee dot name. So this is the
receiver name right after that you can
add other details like task title. So we
can write like this
back
dollar sign curly braces
task dot title
remove this comma from here.
So we have added hi and receiver name.
Then we have added the task title and
then we will add some other text. We can
also add the task description like this
task dot description. We can add the due
date also like I'll add here
back
dollar sign curly braces
task dot due date.
Next we need to convert this date into a
date format. So I'll just cut this one
and here we'll add new date
and in this one provide this task dot
due date and after that we'll add to
local date string and call this
function. So it will display the due
date. We can also send the origin or URL
so that the user can come to this portal
after seeing this email. So to display
that URL you can use the anchor link. So
we can use the a tag
like this. And in this one we can add
the text called view task. And then we
will add the href property here.
And in this HDF we can insert the URL.
For that we can use dollar sign curly
braces and provide the origin.
That's it. So we can send the message
like this. But I want to make it
professional. So we have already
prepared one HTML template for this. So
I'll just remove this one. And here
we'll add these data in a HTML template.
So we have added the data. Here you can
see we have added a div and added some
style property. Then we have added the
receiver name. Then we have added the
task title. After that we have added
task description and due date. Then we
have added the origin in a tag. And here
we have the message. Please make sure to
review and complete it before the due
date.
So this function will send an email to
assignee or receiver with their name
then task title then due date then task
description and URL and this text
message. Now this ingest function will
add another function also that will be
sleeping. It means it will be a
scheduled function. So I'll just come
here and uh after sending this email
here we'll add if statement
and we will check for the today's date
and if the today's date is not equal to
due date then we will add another
function that will be scheduled to
trigger on due date. So here we'll add
new date.
Let me just copy from here
and paste it here. New date
task dot due date to local string
not equal to
new date
to data string. Here we have added two
local data string and this is the two
data string. So here we are checking if
the today's date is not equal to due
date. So in this case we'll add await
a step dot sleep until
and in this one let's add the ID
wait for the due date.
Right? Then we'll add comma here and
provide
new date
and the new date will be
the task dot
due date.
Right? So this function will sleep until
due date
and when the due date comes it will
execute a function. So let's add a
weight
a step dot run
and uh here we will check for the task
whether the task is completed or not. So
let's add check if task is completed. If
the task is completed we will not do any
action. But if the task is still pending
we will send the reminder email. So I'll
write a sync add function
in this one. First we'll get the task
data. So let's add const
task equal to await
prisma dot
task dot
find unique.
In this one, let's add where
id and the id is task ID,
right? And after that, we'll add include
and we will include the
assigne. It will be true. And then we
will include the project.
Let's make it true.
And uh after that
here let's add the if statement. If not
of task. So if the task is not available
then let's add return. So it will not do
anything. Now let's add another if
statement. And here we'll add the task
dot
a status property not equal to
done. So if the task is not done yet, it
means the task is pending. So in this
condition, we have to send another email
that will be reminder email. So I'll
write await
a step dot run.
And uh let's add the ID here
send task reminder email. And uh after
that we'll add the async function that
will send the email. So we have added
the async arrow function.
And here let's add await and we will use
the sender function that is send email
function. So let's add send email.
And here we have to add the data like
two. So in this two we will provide the
task dot assigne dot email.
it means the receiver email. Then we'll
add the subject again. So I'll write the
subject here in tactics. So it will be
reminder for
project name reminder for task.t
project.name. Right? And after that we
have to add the data in body property.
So let's add comma
body. And here we will add the HTML
template. You can add the data in simple
text format also. So I have already
created the HTML template for email. So
I'll paste it here. So in this one you
can see we have added the div. Then we
have added the H2 tag. In this H S2 tag
we have added the receiver name. Then we
have added the project name. Then we
have added the P tag with task title.
Then we have added another div and in
this one we have added the task
description and due date.
After that we have added the link to
view the task and after that we have
added this message. Please make sure to
review and complete it before the due
date. That's it. So this email will be
sent on the due date if the task is
still pending. So we have created this
ingest function that will send the email
whenever the task is created and it will
send another reminder email on the due
date if the task is still pending.
So now let's export it here. So I'll
write comma and provide this function
send task assignment email. Right? So we
have added this function in this
functions array. So now we have added
all the functionality. Next we have to
deploy it so that we can sync our
application in the ingest. So let's
click on this source control icon.
And here we have to add the commit
message. But before that we have missed
one more thing. We have created the
ingest function. But this ingest
function is not triggered yet. So I'll
just come here in the task controller.
We have the task controller.js JS file
in this one we have created this
controller function create task right so
after creating the task we have to send
the email right so let's come here
scroll down you can see the task has
been created in the database and in the
task we have added the assigne data and
just before this sending response let's
send the email also so here we'll add
await
and use the ingest
So just import the ingest from the
ingest folder index.js
file
right. So you can see
ingest has been imported from the
ingest/index.js
file and after that
here we will use dot send. In this send
method we'll add the object and provide
the name. So in this name we will add
the event name that is app/
task assigned
right and after that we have to send the
data also. So let's add the data
property and in this data property let's
add the
task ID and in this task id we'll
provide task dot id then we'll add the
comma and provide the origin
like this. So here it will trigger the
ingest function and uh it will send this
event app task dot assigned and it will
pass this data task id and origin and it
will be received here in this ingest
function.
You can see this is the
event name app/task dot assigned and
here we'll receive the task ID and
origin so that it will send the email
whenever a new task is created. After
that let's upload the code on GitHub. So
click on this source control.
Here we'll add the message.
So we'll add the message here backend
complete.
and click on commit button
then sync changes.
So it will update the code on our GitHub
repo.
It's done. Now let me just come back to
the GitHub profile and uh open this
repository. Let me refresh it. So you
can see just now we have committed the
changes.
Correct. And uh after that it will
automatically redeploy our project. If I
come to deployments,
it is redeploying the project but it
will give an error because we have not
updated the environment variables. So
I'll come to settings then come to
environment variables and uh here you
can see we have these environment
variable. We have added the
node environment then color then we have
the
database URL direct URL and ingest right
and uh after that I'll just come here
and open our env file
so in this one you can see after inest
we have added these environment
variables so I'll just copy this one
also and Then let's paste it here
in this key.
So we have added the key and value like
this. So we have the sendered email,
SMTP user and SMTP password. Then click
on save.
After that click on redeploy.
Let's click on view deployment.
So you can see the project is getting
redeployed.
So now you can see the status ready
correct. If I open this URL
here also you can see server is live. So
back end is successfully redeployed and
after that we will sync our inest
application. So I'll open the ingest
dashboard. Right now you can see we have
total seven functions right and after
that click on this
project management and then click on
this sync button in the top right corner
then click here sync app.
Now you can see here we have total eight
functions. So the new function is added
here. Let me show you that send task
assignment email. You can see here we
have one more function send task
assignment email that we have just
created.
So finally we have completed the back
end of our project management
application. Now we have to link all the
backend APIs with this front end so that
we can enable the project creation. Then
we can enable the task creation and
comment on the task. And we can also
enable the invitation of team member in
a project.
In this dashboard, we have already
integrated the user authentication
feature. Using that we are logged in,
right? And we have also integrated the
organization feature so that we can
create the organization or workspace.
We can click here to create multiple
workspace.
And now let's start with this dashboard
where we have to display the user's
name. Right now you can see welcome back
user. So instead of this user we will
display the user's name. After that we
will display these data in the
dashboard. Right? Now you can see all
the data is zero. Right? So these are
the data coming from the assets. Now let
me just come back to the VS code
and we'll close all the files. So right
click here and select close saved. After
that in the sidebar we have this server
folder. So let's hide this and we will
expand the client folder because we have
to update the code in the client
project. Right now in this client you
can see we have the pages folder and in
this pages we have dashboard.jsx
file. Let's open this dashboard file. In
this one you can see we have the user
variable and we have added one object
with full name user. Now instead of this
one we will get the user data from
color. We will write import
curly braces use user
from
and here we'll add at color/color
react.
Now let's add this use user here. So
we'll get this user from
use user function.
Right? And in this one we'll get the
full name property.
Right? Now after that if I open the web
page here you can see let me refresh it.
It should display the user's name here.
to display the user's full name here.
I'll just come back and let me add this
user in curly braces because in this
datab we will get the user property
right it will be one object and in that
one we'll get the user property and in
that user property we will get the full
name now let's save the changes and come
back here so you can see here we have
the full name welcome back great stack
right after that we have these data like
total projects, completed project, my
task and overdue. Right? So, we have
added it in a component. If I scroll
down, you can see here we have this
a stats grid, right? We have the stats
grid component. So, let's open this
component.
I'll open this sidebar components folder
and open the stats grid component.
Now in this one you can see we have this
function a stats grid. So first we are
getting the current workspace
right and uh after that here we have the
state variable where we have added the
initial values like total number of
projects, active projects completed, my
task and overdue issues. Right? And
after that we have the a stat cards
right and then
here we have the use effect and in this
use effect we have added a function.
So here we are checking if current
workspace is true then we will set the
data using this set a states right
and in this one we have added the total
projects. So the total projects are
current workspace dot projects.length.
Then we have the active projects. It is
also current workspace dot projects dot
filter. So we will filter out the active
projects here. Then we have the
completed projects. Then my task right.
And then we have overdue issues. So
these data is coming from the current
workspace. And current workspace is
already selected here.
Right, we can choose the current
workspace from here
and it will display the data using that
workspace.
Now next we have this button that is new
project. If I click here, it is opening
this window to create a new project.
Right? So let me show you this
component also. I'll just come back here
and uh if I come to this dashboard you
can see we have this
button
right and uh in this button we have
added new project
right and it is opening the
popup. So here we have added on click
set is dialogue open.
So when it is true then it will open
create project dialogue
right.
So let's open this component. I'll open
this sidebar
and here we have the create project
dialogue dot jsx file. So in this file
you can see we have the current
workspace. It is also selected from the
state using this use selector. And after
that we have added the estate variable
where we have added the properties like
name, description, a status of the
project. And when we will enter the data
in the form, it will get saved in this
estate. Right? And after that we have to
update this data in the database. For
that here we have added this
handle submit function. Right? So we
have to complete this function. In this
one, let's add
try catch a statement. And in this try
block, let's add the if statement. And
we'll add not of
form data.
You can see here we have the form data.
Right? So when the form data dot
team lead property is not true, right?
So in this case we will add return
and provide the toast.
We are not getting the suggestion here.
So we have to display the toast
notification.
If I open the
package dojson file. So in this one you
can see we have the react hot toast
already installed. Right? So this
package is available. So I'll just come
back here and let me import it manually.
So here we'll write
import toast from
react hot toast and after that let's
come here and we'll type toast
dot
error and here we'll add the message
please select a team lead
right and after that let's use the
setter function
set is submitting true.
So you can see here we have the is
submitting
a state. So we will make it true. And
after that we'll add the API call. So
let's add con
curly braces
data
equal to await and then we will use the
API. Let's import this API. You can see
in this client project, we have added
the API.js file, right? So from this
file, we will import the API. Let's add
API and import it from the config
folder. It has been imported. After
that, we'll add
dot post method. And then we have to add
the path of this API endpoint. So it is
/ API/ projects. Using that we can
create a new project. Then we'll add the
comma here and provide the project data.
So I'll write the
workspace ID
and in this workspace ID let's provide
the current workspace
dot id. After that we have to add comma
and spread operator. We will provide
this form data right and after that we
have to authenticate our request. So
just add curly braces and authorization
property.
In this authorization we have to provide
the back text be error
and provide the token. So to provide the
token here we'll add dollar sign curly
braces and let's add await
get token. So first we have to use the
get token from the color. So I'll scroll
up and uh
here
let's add const
curly braces
get token function and get it from the
use o and use o has been imported from
the color/color react right now just
call it here
we'll add get token
So it will authenticate our API request.
Correct? And after that
here we have to call the
function that will add a new project in
the estate. Right? So if I come here and
uh open this
features in this features we have the
workspace slice. In this one
you can see we have the
function called add project right so we
have to use this to add a new project
correct so I'll just come back here in
our create project dialogue and first we
will import the dispatch here so
let's add con
dispatch
equal to
use dispatch and import it from the
react redux
right and uh after that come here in
this API call and after this API call
we'll add dispatch
and provide the add project
and in this add project let's add the
data dot project
so From this API call we'll get the data
in the response and in this data we'll
get the project property. So it will
store the project data in the estate and
after that we have to set the submitting
a state false. Right? So let's copy and
paste it here and here we'll make it
false.
Right? And uh after that let's come here
in the catch block. In this catch block
we'll add the toast notification. So
let's add toast dot error
and here let's provide the
error dotresponse dot data dot message.
We have added the question mark also.
Then we'll add the or operator and
provide the error dot message property.
Right now we'll add finally
and in this block let's set the
is submitting false
right and here we will not make it false
here we will use the setter function to
close this
submit form so let's use the setter
function set
is dialog
open and make it false. So it will close
this dialogue or popup to create a new
project after submitting the form.
So after adding it, let's test our
functionality.
To test this add project feature, we
will come back to the web browser
and let's click on this button add
project or new project. Here also we can
click it will open the same popup. Right
now here we have to add the project
name. So let me add a project name here
launchpad CRM. Then we'll add one small
description. So we have added one
description here. Let's add the status
active. Here we'll add the priority
medium. Then we'll set the start date.
So let's set the start date today. And
we'll set the end date. I'll set
31st. And after that choose the project
lead. So I'll use this email ID. Right
now we have only one user in this
workspace. So we have selected the
project lead and it is also added in the
team member. Right now click on this
create project button.
It says unauthorized. So let me fix it.
We will come back to the VS code. And uh
in this one you can see we have created
this API call right. Let me add this
space here. So you can see in this API
call we have added this path then we
have added the data in this object and
after that we have provided this
authorization. So this authorization
property should be provided in the
headers. Right? So let me just fix it.
I'll just cut this one.
And first we'll add the object with
headers property.
And in this headers property we will
provide this object that contains the
authorization be error and this await
get token. Now save the changes and come
back here. And now I'll click on this
button to add a new project. So click
this button create project.
You can see creating in this button text
and after that add project is not
defined. So let me check this one also.
We will just come back to the VS code.
You can see we have added this add
project here. But we have to import it,
right? So I'll just scroll up and here
let's add import
curly braces add project and let's
import it from
double dot / features folder/
workspace
that is workspace slice. So in this
feature folder we have the workspace
slice file. Now it will be available
right and after that I'll just come back
and click on this button again.
Now you can see creating
and now you can see the project has been
created. You can see total projects one
right completed zero my task zero
overdue zero. Let me refresh it.
So here you can see we have two projects
because we have attempted the project
creation multiple times. First time it
got created but it is not added in the
estate right because we have not
imported it. That's why we have created
two projects here. So let me delete it.
I'll just come back to the database
and uh let's come here in the project
and you can see we have two project with
the same name right so let me delete one
of it
and I'll just come back here let me
refresh it so you can see we have
one project and it is displayed here in
this project overview also
Right now, let me try to add one more
project. I'll click on this button and
then I'll add the project name.
Then we'll add the project description.
Here we will choose the status planning.
Then priority medium. Then we'll set the
start date
and end date. And after that
let's choose the project lead and click
on create project.
So it is also created. You can see total
projects two and here we have overview
and in this overview we have two
projects. In this one you can see the
status is planning and in this one you
can see the status active. If I click on
this project you can see we have these
details like total task completed in
progress and team member. So right now
we have only one member correct. Now in
this one we can create the task. Here
you can see we have this button create
task. If I click here we have to add the
details and we can create the task. So
we have to integrate this functionality.
We will integrate the create task API in
this form.
So I'll just come back to the VS code.
But before creating the task, let me add
multiple members in this workspace so
that we can assign the task to any user.
So I'll just cancel this and first let's
come here in this
dashboard and in this dashboard
we have the team right and in this one
you can see we have total
member one active project two and total
task zero and here we have the user's
name Right. And this user is admin. Now
let's click on this button invite
member.
So here we have this popup or model
window. Using that we can invite the
members in this workspace. So to invite
the members first we have to add the
functionality in this popup or model
window. So just come back to the VS code
and let's open the sidebar then
components. In this components we have
the
invite member dialogue. Let's open it.
We have the invite member dialogue dot
JSX file right and uh in this one
you can see we have this handle submit
function right. So in this handle
subummit function let's use the set
function set is submitting true.
So when we click on the button it will
make it true and after that we will add
the try catch statement and in this try
block
let's add a weight and here we will use
the
organization
and we have to import the organization
from use organization. So I'll scroll up
and let's add con
curly braces organization equal to use
organization and the use organization
has been imported from the color
correct. Now let's come here and here we
can use the organization
dot
invite member and after that here we
have to provide the email address. So
let's add the email address and it will
be
form data
do email
and after that we have to provide the
role. So let's add the role and in this
role let's add the form data
dot ro property.
That's it. And after that we will
display the toast notification. So I'll
write toast
dot
success. And here we'll add the message
called invitation sent successfully.
like this and after that let's use the
setter function
set dialog open and make it false. So it
will close this dialogue.
Now come to the catch block. In this
catch block we'll add the console log.
So let's add console log.
Here we'll add this error.
After that we'll add the toast
notification. So I'll write toast dot
error. And here let's provide error dot
response dot data dot message or error
dot message. Then we'll add the finally
block here.
And in this one let's use the setter
function set is submitting
and make it false.
That's it. And after that if I come back
and let's add any email id here to
invite any user. So I'll write another
email id here
and we will choose the role member and
click on send invitation.
You can see invitation sent
successfully. Right now let me open my
email ID. If this user is already a
member then it will be added in this
organization. And if the user is not
signed up on this application, they will
receive the email. So I'll just open
that email.
You can see we have received the email
like this invitation to join greatest
active and click on this button accept
invitation.
Now let me sign in with my Google
account. I'll choose this. After that
click on this continue button.
So now we are logged in and after that
we are not redirected to the homepage.
So we have to add the redirect URL.
So I'll come back to the color dashboard
and in this one go to configure
and in the left side you will find this
path.
We have paths. Let's open it. And here
you can see we have to add the fallback
development host.
Right? So let's add the URL. I'll just
copy this localhost 5173 and paste it
here
like this. Then click on save. So after
sign up, it will open this URL.
Now let me just come back here and uh
if I open the local host 5173,
it is asking to sign in. So let me sign
in with my Google account. So after sign
up you can see we are redirected to this
dashboard where you can see we are the
member of this great stack dev workspace
and in this workspace we have two
project you can see the user profile
here the name and email id and here also
you can see welcome back abinach kumar
right now I'll just come back to the
previous account who is the admin of
this workspace so in this one you can
see we have the team and in this team
you can see we have two members right
one is admin one is member
and so this invite member is working
fine after that let's add other
functions in this project so I'll come
to this projects then open any project
I'll just open this one and here we can
display the list of task then calendar
then analytics and then settings so in
this settings you can
We have the project details like name,
description, a status, priority, start,
end date and progress. So we have to add
the functionality here to update the
project details.
For that we will come back to the VS
code.
In this one, let's open the client
folder then src then components and here
we will find project setting component.
So here we have the project settings JSX
file. In this one, we have this form
data, right? But before this form data,
let's add const
dispatch.
So let's add dispatch equal to
use dispatch
and it will get imported from the
React Redux. After that let's add con
curly braces get token function and we
will get this function from
use o use o has been imported here from
the color
right after that let's scroll down and
here we have this handle submit function
using that we can update the project
settings or project data so in this one
let's add
set is submitting and make it true. And
after that, let's add toast.
Import it. We'll add toast dot
loading.
And here we'll add the text called
saving.
So it will display this toast
notification until it saved the data.
Here we'll add try catch block
and in this try block we'll make the API
call. So let's add con curly braces data
equal to
await and we will use the API
import it from the config folder
dotput method.
We have used the put method to create
this API endpoint. Now provide the path
that is / API/
projects. Then we'll add the
form data here.
And after that let's add the headers
property
and uh in this headers property we will
add the object and provide the
authorization
and in this authorization we will add
verror await get token function. Right
after that let's use the setter function
set is dialogue open and make it false.
So it will close the popup and after
that let's add dispatch and in this one
we will use the fetch workspaces
and here let's add curly braces
get token function right after that
we'll display the toast notification so
let's add toast dot success
and here we'll add the message that we
will receive from the API that is data
dot message. But before that we have to
dismiss the previous toast notification.
So let's add toast dot
dismiss all.
That's it. And after that come here in
the catch block. In this catch block
again add this toast dot dismiss all.
And here we'll add the toast
dot error.
And in this one, let's add the error dot
response dot data dot message or error
dot message. Then we'll add the finally
block. In this one, let's use the setter
function set is submitting and make it
false.
That's it. So we have added the
functionality here so that we can update
the project settings.
Right? And after that, let me just come
back to the web browser.
And here, let's update this project. So,
I'll write Launchpad CRM
project
like this. And click on save changes.
We'll update this progress. Click on
save changes. You can see saving
and project updated successfully. So, it
has been updated. You can see the
updated project name. Then we have the
progress. If I come back here in this
projects
and you can see in this one the project
name has been updated and you can see
the progress also. Let's open it.
Go to settings. So here we have the
updated project data. So it is working
fine. Next we have to add the team
member in this project.
Till now we have added the team member
in this workspace. Right? Now we'll add
the team member in this particular
project.
Right? So you can see here we have this
button. Let's click here. So it will
open this popup add member to project.
And here we can choose the email ID that
is the user's email ID who is available
in this workspace. Right? So if the user
is available in this workspace, user is
a member of this workspace, then we'll
get the list here and we can add that
member in this particular project. So we
have to add the functionality in this
button that is add member. So I'll just
come back to the VS code. Here we will
open this sidebar. In this components
you will find this add project
member.jsx file. Now in this one you can
see we have this search patterns and
from this search patterns we will find
the ID that will be the project ID. If I
open this page so in this URL you can
see we have this ID right. So this is
the project ID. Now just come back here
and uh after that here we will get the
token. So let's add con
curly braces
get token
equal to use o
and after that we will get the dispatch
function. So just add const
dispatch
equal to use dispatch
like this. So you can see
use dispatch has been imported here and
use o is also imported correct. After
that here we have the current workspace
then we have the
project then is adding a state and then
we have the handler function handle
submit. Right now in this one let's add
setter function set is adding and make
it true.
And after that here we'll add the try
catch a statement.
In this try block we'll add await
API import the API from configs folder.
Then we'll add dot post method. And in
this one let's add the API path. So it
will be / API/ projects. We have added
the back ticks here so that we can
insert the template literal. So just add
dollar sign curly braces. And here we
have to add the project id. So let's add
the project dot id property
right and after that we'll add / add
member.
So this is the API endpoint.
Correct? After that we'll add comma and
here we have to add the email id. So
this email id will be added in this
project. After that we'll add the
headers property here and in this
headers
we will add the authorization
be error and token to authenticate this
request. Now let's add the toast
notification. So I'll write toast
dot success
and provide the message added to project
successfully.
Then we will add the setter function
set is dialogue open and make it false.
So it will close this popup. And after
that let's update our state also. So
let's add dispatch
and we'll add the
fetch workspaces.
And in this one let's add the get token
function.
Right.
And uh after that come here in the catch
block. In this catch block just add the
toast dot error
and in this error we'll provide the
error dotresponse dot data dossage or
error dot message. Then we will add the
finally block
and in this finally block let's use the
setter function set is adding and make
it false.
That's it. Now after that let me open
the web page and click on this button
and choose this email id and click on
add member.
You can see adding
and now you can see the notification
added to project successfully and after
that it will refresh the web page and
here you can see team members. In this
one we have two members right this is
the first one and this is the second
one. So now we can add a new member in
this project. It is working fine.
Now we will add the functionality to
create a new task. So I'll just come
back here in the another account.
So in this account
we have the projects right. And uh if I
come to this projects and open this one
here you can see we are getting this
button new task. If I click here it is
opening this popup to create a new task.
So to make it functional, I'll just come
back to the VS code
and uh after that let's open the sidebar
and uh in this components you will find
this file
create task dialogue.jsx JSX
right and uh in this one we have the
current workspace
then we have the project then we have
the team members
right and before that let's get the
get token so that we can make the API
call so I'll write con
curly braces
get token
equal to
use o. So use o has been imported. After
that we'll get the dispatch function
also. So let's add const dispatch equal
to
use dispatch.
Use dispatch has been imported here.
Correct. After that you can see we have
the state is submitting and then we have
the form data that will be submitted to
add a new task. Then we have this handle
submit function. So we have to complete
this function to submit the task and
store it in the database. So here let's
use the setter function set is
submitting true.
After that we will make the API call. So
I'll write the try catcher statement and
in this try block we'll add con curly
braces data
equal to and here we will add await API
import the API from the config folder
then dot post method
here we have to add the API endpoint it
will be / API/ tasks
then we have to add the data so I'll
write curly braces a spread operator we
will use
form data and comma workspace id
and in the workspace id let's provide
the current workspace
dot id after that we will add the
project ID also so let's add the project
ID
after that we have to authenticate our
request so here we'll add the headers
property
And in the headers we have to add
authorization then v error and this
token. After that let's use this set
function set. So create task and make it
false so that it will hide the popup
and after that we will reset the form.
So here let's add
set form data
and in this one we will add the object
and provide these properties that will
reset the form again. So we will provide
the title, description, type, a status,
priority, assigne ID and due date. After
that we will display the toast
notification. So let's add toast import
the toast from react hot toast. Then
we'll add dot success. And after that
let's add the data dot message. So we
will display the success message that we
will receive from the API response.
After that here we will add dispatch.
And in this one let's add the add task
function. So first we have to import it.
Let's scroll up
here. We will add import
curly braces and provide
add task
from
and here we'll add
/
features folder/workspace
slice.
Now let's add this add task here in this
dispatch.
After that here we will add the data. So
let's add
data dot task
like this. So it will update the task in
the state also. After that come to this
catch block and in this catch block
again we have to add the toast
notification. So we have added this
toast dot error. After that we'll add
the finally and in this one let's use
the setter function set is submitting
and make it false.
That's it. So we have completed this
function
using that we can create a new task.
Right now we have to test it. So I'll
just come back to the web browser
and uh in this project we will create
the task. Right? So
I'll add the data like title. This is
the task title. Then we'll add the task
description. So here we'll add small
description. Then we'll add the type.
Right? So here let me choose the
type. It is
task. We can choose the bug feature
improvement and other. Right? Let's
choose the priority. It will be medium.
And here we'll add the assigne. So let's
choose the user to whom you want to
assign this task. So let me use this
user. And here we'll add the status
in progress.
And after that let's choose the due
date. So I'll choose the due date after
3 days. And click on create task button.
It is creating right. You can see the
text in the button. Now you can see the
notification task created successfully.
So here you can see in this project we
have one task and the completed task is
zero in progress one and we have two
members in this
project. Right here we have the task
title. Then the type is task. The
priority is medium and the status is in
progress. And this is the assigne
details and due date.
Right now let me create one more task
here.
So I'll click on this button new task.
Here we'll add
the title.
Then we'll add the small description.
And here we'll choose the type. So in
this type let me provide
improvement. Right? And here also we'll
choose the priority medium and assign to
the same person. And here also we'll add
in progress and assign the due date and
click on create task.
Now another task has been assigned.
Right here we have selected the type
but it is not selected. So let me add
one more here.
We will check it.
Let's add the title. Then we'll choose
the description.
And then we'll choose the
type
feature.
And let's choose the priority and assign
to this user in progress and due date.
Create task.
It is created. And in all task the type
is task only.
Let me refresh it.
So we have to fix this one.
I will just come back to the VS code and
let me open the sidebar and let's come
to this server folder. In this server we
have the task controller. In this task
controller we have created this
controller function create task. In this
one you can see here we have added the
task equal to await prisma dot
task.create. So it will create the data
in database. Here we have added these
details but we have not added the type.
So let's add the space. Provide the type
that is the task type and provide the
comma save the changes. Right? And after
that if I create a new task then it will
also update the type. So let me just
come back to the database and come to
this task
and let me delete the task from here.
I'll delete two task
and come back here. Refresh it.
You can see we have one task. The type
is task priority medium. Right now let's
click on this button to create a new
task. And after that here we will add
the details like title.
Then we will add the description here.
After that we will add the type
improvement. Then we'll set the priority
low. Then assign the user.
Then in progress and after that let's
add the due date and create task.
So the task has been created. And you
can see here we have the type
improvement.
Right? And if I click on any task, it
will display the details like this.
Right? In the right side, we have the
task name. Then in progress,
improvement, low, this is the
description. And here we have the user
to whom this task is assigned. And this
is the due date. And this is the project
details also. Right? Now just come back
and I'll add one more task here. So I'll
just click on this button and here we'll
add the new task name. So it is client
feedback integration.
After that we'll add the description
here.
Then we'll add the type. So let's add
the type feature. Then priority is
medium. Assign the user and in progress
and due date.
create task.
So you can see the another task the type
is feature right and here we have the
assigne details. So this create task is
working fine right now let me just click
here so it will display the details like
this
and after that we have to add the
feature to update the task and delete
the task.
Let's come back to this page and now
we'll add the functionality to update
and delete the task.
But before we add these features, let me
verify the task is assigned to a new
user or not. So I'll just come back to
the another user
and
in this another account
you can see we have the another account
here. Right? And if I refresh it,
it should display the task here. It is
not added.
My task is zero. If I come to projects
in this project, we have the task. But
in my task, it is showing zero.
I will just come back to the VS code and
open the sidebar. In this side, you will
find this my task sidebar. JSX file. And
in this one you can see we have the user
equal to object and provided one id. So
let me remove it. And here we will add
con curly braces user equal to use user
from color. So now we have the user
data. Right? After that you can see this
function fetch user task right. So in
this one it will find the user ID using
this user dot id and for this user id it
will find the task in the current
workspace task right. So just save the
changes and come back here. Now you can
see in this profile where we have
assigned the task we have the tasks
right we have the three task. Let me
refresh it.
Still you can see we have total three
task here. If I click here, it will
display the task details.
If I click on anyone, it will display
the detail of this task. Right?
So it is working fine.
And now let me check the feature to send
the task email. Right? So whenever the
task is assigned, it will send an email
also. So I'll check my email.
So in this email you can see we have
received multiple emails because we have
sent the task multiple times right we
have created three task. So here we have
the name then the message then the task
name and description and due date right
so this email feature is also working
fine we can receive the email whenever a
task is assigned after that I'll just
come back here
in another account so in this account we
have
these task and in the right side we have
the details right now let Let me just
add the functionality to update the
status from here. We can change the
status like done or in progress. Right?
So I'll just come back to the VS code
and after that let's open this file
project task from this sidebar.
We have the project task.jsx JSX file,
right? And uh in this one you can see we
have this function called
handle delete
right so that we can delete the task and
uh before that we have this function
handle a status change
right so in this one we have to make the
API call to change the status whenever
the status is changed it will update the
status in database
To make the API call in this file, first
we need the token, right? So let's
scroll up. So I'll write const curly
braces
get token
equal to
use o and use o has been imported from
color.
Now we have this get token function so
that we can generate the token and after
that let's come here
in this handle a status change here we
have toast.loading loading and after
that we have this comment right so let
me remove it
and remove this
await and here let's add await
API
import the API from the config folder
then dotput method
then we'll add the API endpoint that is
/ API/ tasks and after that here we'll
add slash
dollar sign curly braces s and provide
the task id
after that let's add the comma and here
we'll add the object and provide the a
status here so in this a status
we will send the new status whichever is
selected right and uh after that let's
add comma and provide the object in this
one we'll add the headers to
authenticate the request. So in the
headers we have added authorization,
beer and token.
But before that let's generate the token
here. So
here let's add const
token equal to await and get token
function and this token is provided in
this API request right so it will update
the status
and after that let's come here in this
handle delete function in this one also
we have to make the API call so first
here you can see we have confirmation to
delete the task and after that we will
generate the token here. So let's add
const
token equal to
await
get token function. Now after that we
will add this toast.loading
deleting task and after that here we
will make the API call right. So let's
remove it and we'll write await
API dot
post
and after that we'll provide the API
endpoint that is / API/ task/delete
and after that let's add the data here
that is the task id
and in the task ID we will add the
selected task. tasks right and after
that authenticate the request using the
headers. So let's add the headers here
and in the headers we have added
authorization beer and token and after
that it will call this delete task and
provided the selected task right and uh
we have completed this function also and
after that let's save the changes and
come back here. So right now you can see
we have this a status in progress. If I
change it to done,
you can see a status updated. Task
updated successfully. Right? Task a
status updated successfully.
If I refresh it.
So here you can see it is displaying the
a status done in this last one. Now
let's update this one also. Client
feedback. Let's make it done
and refresh it.
You can see the client feedback
integration is done. So we can update
the task. It will get saved in the
database. Now let's test the delete
functionality also. So I'll just check
this one. You can see the dots here.
I'll just click here. So it will display
this delete button and click on this
delete. It is asking are you sure you
want to delete selected task. Click
okay. You can see deleting task and it
has been deleted. If I refresh it
now you can see
all the tasks are deleted. So let me fix
it here. All the tasks got deleted. To
fix it I'll just come back to the VS
code. And in this handle delete function
in this API call we are sending the task
id but it should be task ids. Make sure
to add this s also just update this task
ids. Save the changes. Now I'll just
come back here and here we'll add other
task. So let me add the task here.
Now I'll click here to add a new task
and I will pause the video and add three
task.
So here we have added three task. Now
let me delete one of it. I'll just
select the second one
and click on delete and okay.
So one task has been deleted. If I
refresh it still we have two task. Let
me show you that.
it is removed. Let's check it.
I'll come back to the VS code. You can
see in this API call, we are sending the
task ids. But if I open the controller
file, we'll come back to the server task
controller. And in this one, you can see
we are receiving the data from body and
it is tasks ID. Here also we have s
right. So let me just copy this one
tasks id. And after that let's come here
and provide it here.
Provide this task ids. Let's save the
changes again. Update it and save the
changes. And again I'll just come back
here and we'll add three new task. So
I'll use this form and I will pause the
video and add the task.
So we have added three task. Let me
select the second one and click on
delete.
Okay.
And now I'll refresh the web page.
Now we have two tasks available. It is
working fine. Right now you can see the
status todo and todo. Now let me change
the status. I'll choose done.
So you can see the status has been
updated. Here we have completed one and
in progress one right and here we have
total two tasks and total two members.
So this task feature is working fine. We
can update the task. We can display the
list of task and we can delete the task.
After that if I open the dashboard
here you can see we have total two
projects. We have zero completed
projects. We have one task right in this
my task we have only one task create new
logo concept and here we have overdue
zero. If I come back to the second
account if I refresh it in this one you
can see we have one task client feedback
integration. Right? So we have assigned
this task to this person. Now I'll just
come back here. Next, we have to add the
functionality to add the comments on the
task. If I open the
project, then open the task and open the
task detail page. Here we can post the
comment on this task
to add the comment functionality in this
task. Let me just come back to the VS
code
and here we will open this sidebar and
let's open the pages folder and in this
pages we have the task details JSX file.
I'll open this file.
Now in this one you can see we have the
dummy user data right. We have the user
equal to one object and added the ID
user one. So let me remove it. Here we
will get the user from color. So first
let's add the import.
And here we'll add
curly braces
use user and import it from color/color
react. And after that I'll just come
here and we will write con curly braces
user
equal to
use user function. So now we have the
user data here from color and after that
here we will get the get token function
also. So I'll write const
curly braces get token
equal to
use o. So use o has been imported as you
can see in this line. So now we have the
user and get token. After that we can
make the API call to fetch the comment
details. So here we have the function
fetch commands. Right? So in this one
let's add if and I'll write not of task
ID. So when the task ID is not
available, we will stop the execution.
So simply add return.
Now suppose the task ID is available
then we can make the API call. So I'll
write try catch block here. And in this
try block I'll write const
and generate the token. So I'll write
con token equal to
await and get token function.
After that we'll make the API call. So
here we'll get the data in the response.
So let's add curly braces data equal to
await. And we will use the API and
import the API from config folder. Then
we'll add dot get and here we'll add the
path. So I'll write back here and
provide the path / API/
comments and then we have to provide the
task ID. So I'll write dollar sign curly
braces and provide the task ID here.
Then we will add the comma and provide
the headers to authenticate our request.
So in this one I'll write authorization
property and provide the beer and token.
Now here we'll get the data and from
this data we will extract the comments
and use the setter function set comments
and in this one let's provide the data
dot
comments property
and if it is not available then we'll
add odd operator and provide empty array
like this. Now come to the catch block.
In this catch block we'll display the
toast notification. So import the toast
then write dot error
and here I'll write error dot response
dot data dot message or
we will provide error dot message.
So we have added the functionality to
fetch the comments from the database
using the API. Right after that scroll
down and uh here you will find this
function handle add comment. So using
this function we can add a new comment.
Right? So first it will trim the entered
text that is entered in the
input field. Then we have the try catch
block. In this try block we'll add the
notification adding comment. And here we
have to make the API call. Right. So
I'll just remove this statement
and uh
after that
let's remove this one also that is dummy
comment and here we'll make the API
call. So I'll write con
token equal to
await get token and then we will add con
curly braces data equal to await then
API
dot post method because we have to post
the comment and we have created the API
using this post method. Now we'll add
the API endpoint. So it will be / API/
comments
like this and after that we will provide
the comma and here we have to provide
the data in this API request. So I'll
add the task id first. So the task id
will be
task dot id. After that we'll add comma
provide the content.
we have to send the content property and
in this content let's add
new comment.
So it will be sent on API. After that
here we have to authenticate the
request. So let me just copy this
statement
this headers. I'll just copy this and
paste it here. So we have added headers
authorization beer and token. Now we
have this data
right and after that let's use the
setter function set commands and in this
one we will provide the previous data
and it will return one array with
previous data and with that we will also
add the added command that is
data dot comment property
correct. Then we have setter function
that will reset the new comment. Then we
will display the toast notification that
is comment added and before that we will
dismiss all the other to notification.
And here we have the catch block also.
So we have added the functionality to
add a new comment and fetch the command.
After that let me just come back to the
web page and uh let me refresh it.
So here we have this input field. In
this one, let me add a message. All
right.
I am working on it. And click on this
post button. You can see adding comment.
And now you can see the comment has been
added here. I am working on it. If I
refresh it,
you can see it will fetch the comment.
So we can fetch the comments on this
task and we can also post a new comment.
So this comment feature is also working
fine.
After that if I come to dashboard
in the right side you can see we have
the task summary right. So right now we
don't have any data here in this summary
in the right sidebar. So let me complete
this one also. I'll just come back here.
I'll open the components. In this
components you will find
task summary.jsx
file right and uh in this one
you can see we have the user and it is
the dummy user ID right. So here let me
replace it. I'll write const
curly braces user
equal to use user and the use user has
been imported from color
right now after that I'll just come back
here in this web page
let me refresh it
here we don't have any data in progress
overdue but here in my task we have this
task data, right? So, we have one task
here that is assigned to me and the
another task is assigned to another
person. Right? So, this task summary is
also working.
Right? Next, you can see we have this
settings menu item. Right? If I click
here, nothing is working. Right? So, we
have to add the functionality here so
that when we click here, it will open
the page to edit the profile.
For that I'll just come back to the VS
code and in this
components you will find this
sidebar.jsx
file. Correct. Now in this one
here
let's add con
curly braces and here we will use open
user profile
component and let's get it from use
color and import the use color. So you
can see the use color has been imported
from the color/color react and now we
have the open user profile
function and after that we have to link
this function with our menu item. So
I'll just scroll down. Let me just copy
it and scroll down here.
You can see this button. In this button
you can see the text called settings.
Right? So here we have to add on click
property.
In this on click simply provide this
function open user profile.
Save the changes. Now I'll just come
back here
and click on this settings. So you can
see it is opening this model to edit the
profile. We can update the profile
image, name, email id or we can also go
to security to update the password or
delete the account.
So now we have completed all
functionality in this project management
application.
Now we have to deploy our project
online. So we have already deployed the
back end. Next we will deploy the front
end. So I'll just come back to the VS
code and let me close all the files. So
right click and select close saved.
Then open this sidebar.
And here we will click on this source
control icon. And here we will add the
commit message. So I'll write project
completed
and click on commit button
sync changes.
After that if I open the GitHub
repository and uh let me refresh it.
So you can see we have just committed
the changes in this GitHub repo.
Correct. And after that let me open the
versel dashboard. So this is the project
management backend server. This is the
URL right? Let me open this URL here.
So this is the backend URL for the
project management. Now we have to
deploy the front end. So I'll just come
back here.
and click on this new and choose the
project add new project.
Then we will choose the same repository
project management. And in front of this
repository name I'll click on import.
And after that we will write the project
name here. So it is project management
or let me write project mgt.
And after that let me choose the root
directory. So click on this edit and
here we will choose this client
directory
because we have created the front end in
the client folder. Then click on
continue
and after that let's come here in the
environment variables and here we have
to provide the environment variables for
the front end. So I'll just come back to
the VS code and let's open the client
folder and in this client we have env
file. Let me open it and just copy these
environment variables. Let's copy and
paste it here.
Now here you can see we have the wheat
base URL. So in this base URL right now
we have this local host. So remove this
local host and here we will add the live
URL that is deployed on Versel. So this
is the backend URL deployed on Versel.
So just copy this one and paste it here
in this base URL. And at the end we have
this forward slash. So make sure to
remove this forward slash from the end.
And after that click on this deploy
button.
Let me scroll down and here you can see
the status of this deployment.
So there is some error in this
deployment. So let me check it. In this
error message it says cannot find module
and this is the module name. And then it
says npm has a bug related to optional
dependencies.
And uh again it says please try npmi
again after removing both package
lock.json
and node_modules
directory. So we have to remove this
package lock json. For that let me just
come here in the
GitHub repository then go to client
and after that here you will find this
package log JSON let me delete it I'll
open this one after opening this package
log dojson file just click on this three
dot and choose delete file
after deleting this file you need to
commit the changes So you will find this
button commit changes. Let's click here
and click commit changes.
Now you can see the package lock JSON
file has been removed. After that just
come back to the versal deployment and
go to project.
Then we will go to deployments.
And you can see it is trying to redeploy
the project because we have made changes
in the GitHub repository. So you can see
the status building.
Now you can see the status ready. Let me
click here.
So you can see our project is
successfully deployed. Here's the
project domain. Let me copy this domain
and open in the web browser. So I'll
open it here.
So once you open this web page or
website you will find this login screen
because in this project management you
need to login then you can access the
dashboard. So I'll click on this
continue with Google.
Let me choose the email ID and continue.
So you can see we have successfully
deployed the project and it is working
fine. So we have deployed this project
on Versel. This is the live link.
Now let me just come back to the local
host.
Now let me explore all the features one
by one. So when you log on this
application, you need to create an
organization or workspace. You can
create multiple workspace here and you
can switch between different workspace
from this drop-down. Or you can click
here to create another workspace. You
need to upload the logo and provide the
name.
After creating the workspace, you can
add a new project in the workspace. So
you will find this button new project.
Let's click here. And you need to
provide the project name, description, a
status, priority, and a start and end
date. Then you can choose the project
lead and team member. You can choose
from this drop-down. Right? And if you
want to add a new user in this
workspace then you can go to team and
here you can click on this button invite
member and here you can put the email id
and choose the role and then you can
invite a new user in this workspace and
when the user is available in the
workspace you can add them in the
project also. Right. After creating the
project, you can come here and open any
project and in this project you can go
to settings and you can add new members
in the project also. Right now we have
two members. You can click here on this
plus and you can choose the members from
the drop-down when you have the member
available in the same workspace. So
first we have to add the member in the
workspace and we can add the member in
the project also. After that you can
also update the project details from
this settings. Then you can go to
analytics to see the analytics of this
project. You can see the task by status,
task by type and task by priority. Then
you can go to calendar. In this calendar
you can see the task due date. Right?
And here you can see the upcoming task.
After that here we have the tasks list
and in this one you can see the type
priority a status and assigne details
and due date. You can also update the
status from this drop-down.
You can choose the status like in
progress or done. After that you can
also delete any task. You can click on
this dot and click on this delete button
to delete any task. After that if I open
any task you can add the comments in
this task. Right now we have already
added one comment. You can add the
comment in this input field and click on
post. So this comment will be added in
the task. After that
in the left sidebar you will find the
projects right you can see we have the
list of projects in the sidebar also. So
you can easily access the projects and
you can also access the task from the
sidebar. We have the my task and you can
see we have the drop-down where you can
see the list of task.
After that if I again open this project
in this project you can see we can
create a new task using this button
create task and here you can provide the
task name, description, type, priority
and assigne. You can assign the task to
any member in the project and you can
set the status and due date for the
task. So this is all functionality of
our project management application.
So finally we have completed our full
stack project management application. I
hope this video will be helpful for you.
If you have any question you can ask me
in the comment section. Please like and
share this video and also subscribe my
channel great stack to watch more videos
like this one. Thank you so much for
watching this video.